<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon two books, the one entituled, the case of allegiance to a King in possession the other, an answer to Dr. Sherlock's Case of allegiance to sovereign powers, in defence of the case of allegiance to a King in possession, on those parts especially wherein the author endeavours to shew his opinion to be agreeable to the laws of this land. In a letter to a friend.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58389</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200522</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825070</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29442</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58389)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29442)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2110:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon two books, the one entituled, the case of allegiance to a King in possession the other, an answer to Dr. Sherlock's Case of allegiance to sovereign powers, in defence of the case of allegiance to a King in possession, on those parts especially wherein the author endeavours to shew his opinion to be agreeable to the laws of this land. In a letter to a friend.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Rogers, at the Sun over-against St. Dunstan's Church in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCI. [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an initial license to print leaf with errata at foot.</note>
                  <note>With an advertisment at end of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Browne, Thomas, 1654?-1741. --  Answer to Dr. Sherlock's Case of allegiance to sovereign powers, in defence of the Case of allegiance to a king in possession.</term>
               <term>Browne, Thomas, 1654?-1741. --  Case of allegiance to a king in possession.</term>
               <term>Sovereignty --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Allegiance --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29442:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29442:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> REFLECTIONS Upon Two BOOKS, The One Entituled, The Caſe of Allegiance TO A KING in POSSESSION: The Other, AN ANSWER TO Dr. SHERLOCK'S Caſe of Allegiance to Sovereign Powers, IN Defence of the CASE of ALLEGIANCE to a King in Poſſeſſion, On thoſe Parts eſpecially wherein the Author endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſhew his Opinion to be agreeable to the Laws of this LAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Letter to a Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Kogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> over-againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29442:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29442:2"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS ON The CASE of ALLEGIANCE to a King in Poſſeſſion, <hi>and</hi> The Defence of it.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I could be uneaſy under any of your Commands, this, you may be aſſured, would be the time of my ſhewing it: It is an hard task you have laid upon me; The Books, of which you require my thoughts, are long: and ſpeak the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor (whoever he is) to be a Man of great Learning and Reaſon; one, who can argue to the beſt advantage his Subject will bear. And the Collections he has made, plainly ſhew, that he has taken great pains, and bent all his thoughts for ſome time, to the maintenance of that Cauſe, to which ſome <hi>Prejudice</hi> has unhappily determined him. I, Sir, to your knowledg never ſaw the Books till within theſe very few days, and I fear you will have too much reaſon from what I write to believe me, when I tell you, That the reading the Books once over, (and that with frequent Interruptions too) waſted almoſt half the time I have been able to allow my thoughts upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. This has prevented my conſulting any Books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29442:3"/> in favour of Submiſſion to a King in Poſſeſſion, nay, of reading Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Book, which the <hi>Defence</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to Anſwer. You muſt not therefore be ſuprized, if you happen to meet here with what others have ſaid on the ſame Subject, without any acknowledgment that I received it from them; or (which I more fear) if you ſhould find Opinions differing from thoſe of very great Men, who have undertaken this Controverſy. They were <hi>my Thoughts,</hi> Sir, which you required, and I have taken a courſe to give <hi>them</hi> to you free, neither biaſſed, nor over-ruled by the Opinions or Authority of others.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion, as 'tis ſtated by the Author of <hi>the Caſe,</hi> is put very <hi>cautiouſly</hi> and ſtrongly in favour of the Cauſe he propoſes to himſelf to maintain; he has fenced it in with ſuch Reſtrictions in the ſtating, and the Expoſition of the Terms, that it would be a very unneceſſary thing to undertake an Anſwer to him, if his Book did not offer at the proof of more than the firſt Queſtion under his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations, does require from him.</p>
            <p>No one, I ſuppoſe, who has ſubmitted to Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Government, who thinks it too the <hi>Duty</hi> of all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Men to do the ſame, and to pay Faith and Allegiance to them, will therefore believe himſelf at all concerned to maintain that, <hi>If a Perſon who has no manner of Right, by force, exclude, or depoſe a King, whoſe Right to the Crown is clear and undoubted, and thereby gets the Exerciſe of the Government into his hands, the Regal Authority, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right remaining ſtill in the excluded Prince, the People ought to pay a full and entire Submiſſion and Obedience to this King in Poſſeſſion, ſo as never to attempt any thing againſt him, but ſtand by and defend him againſt the diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed Prince, with his Life and Fortune.</hi> This is a Caſe of our Author's own making, and bears no Reſemblance
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29442:3"/> to the preſent State of this Nation: Nay, on the contrary, if I may take the liberty to reduce the general Queſtion to our particular Caſe, I think the two things agreed by him, as Preliminaries, will ſufficiently juſtify any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man in his ſwearing Allegiance, and paying the Duty <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſe,</hi> f. 2.</note> of a Subject to Their preſent Majeſties. For the firſt of them agrees, <hi>That a bare Poſſeſſion, tho purely by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will carry a Right to the Subjects Allegiance in an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Monarchy, where the whole Royal Line is extinct; to prevent the Bloodſhed and Confuſion which might follow upon the Peoples attempting to ſet up another Perſon or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> This prudential Reaſon, and a Submiſſion upon it, he lays down to be a ſufficient Title to the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and that it makes him <hi>from thenceforth King de Jure,</hi> one to whom all Faith and Allegiance becomes due. ('Tis ſo obvious of it ſelf, that I might ſpare the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, That he frames his Caſe upon a Suppoſition of the whole Royal Lines being extinct, for no other purpoſe than to reſtrain it ſo, as to extend only to Caſes where there is no other Perſon in being, who has a juſt Title to the Crown, and whoſe Right is invaded by that Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion).</p>
            <p>The ſecond agrees, <hi>That where there are divers preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and it is not</hi> clear <hi>who has the true Right or Title; the Subjects Allegiance is to follow the Poſſeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore the late King, <hi>by</hi> the aſſuming to himſelf an Authority to ſuſpend, and by general and unlimited Diſpenſations to repeal Laws without Parliament; <hi>by</hi> the entruſting almoſt the whole Power, Military and Civil, in the hands of ſuch Perſons only as would undertake with their endeavours to ſupport him in thoſe Exceſſes; <hi>By</hi> the putting thoſe few Laws which he found it his intereſt to obſerve, in Execution, by ſuch generally, as were by Law made incapable of all Truſt and Rule; <hi>By</hi> the conſtant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29442:4"/> aim and tendency that every one of his Actions had to enſlave us at home, not to omit the Bonds prepared for us, by his immoveable Adherence to the Intereſts of the <hi>French</hi> King, from which (as a chargeable Experience teaches us) the utmoſt effort we can make, and that aſſiſted with very great and powerful Alliances, will ſcarce reſcue us. <hi>If</hi> his unwearied endeavours to deſtroy the Reformed Religion, with a thouſand other Male-Adminiſtrations, that ſtruck at the very Being and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Conſtitution it ſelf, and the Laws and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of <hi>the People of England;</hi> did declare, that he would not govern by our Laws or Act by an Authority limited by them. <hi>If</hi> upon the Parliaments humble and modeſt Repreſentation to him (according to their Duty) of the unwarrantableneſs of ſuch Proceedings, and the Alarm that the People took at his great Violations of their Rights, and Breaches upon the Government, he broke them up in Anger, and thereby ſhewed an obſtinate and ſetled Reſolution to aſſert that unlimited Power to himſelf, and govern according to it. <hi>If</hi> having by theſe Arbitrary Proceedings drawn great Difficulties upon himſelf, inſtead of taking proper Courſes to ſecure his People againſt ſuch Exceſſes for the future, he held to the ſame Counſels ſtill, and by their Advice quitted the Kingdom, then in the utmoſt Confuſion, without making any Proviſion for the Adminiſtration of the Government, and <hi>voluntarily</hi> put himſelf into the hands of its avowed perpetual Enemy. <hi>If</hi> all theſe things put together, will amount, either to a renouncing and diſclaiming his Title to a Government limited by Laws, or a diſabling and rendring him incapable to Exerciſe any Government at all. Nay, <hi>If</hi> the ſhare and intereſt which the Body of the People have in the Preſervation of the Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and their concern in the welfare of the whole,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29442:4"/> will make it come up but to a doubtful Caſe. <hi>If</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, to reſcue us from thoſe Confuſions, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what remained of the Ancient Government, and to reſtore what had been impaired, the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the People did fill the deſerted Throne by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming the Authors of our Deliverance, King and Queen, and the Body of the People (for the number of Male-contents is ſo inconſiderable, that there is no need of ſoftning the word upon their account) have owned their Title to the Crown, ſubmitted and ſworn Allegiance to them as their Governors: And <hi>if</hi> it be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to the whole World, that their Government has produced all the good Effects that were propoſed or aimed at, and they are in as full and quiet Poſſeſſion of the Throne, as ever any Princes were who ſat upon it, with a repeated Recognition of their Title. I cannot but think, that every one, who will give himſelf leave calmly to conſider, muſt agree, That our Caſe comes up to that which our Author puts. It does not, cannot appear that any other Perſon has a better Right to the Crown: and the conſequence of our Author's drawing from that, will be, That every <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> ought to bear Faith, and pay Allegiance to Their Majeſties, who (thanks be to God) are in ſo full a Poſſeſſion of the Throne.</p>
            <p>But not to enter farther into the general Queſtion, which, I think, ought not to be too freely ſearcht into, leſt it give Advantage and Encouragement to a ſort of People, who will be forward out of Wantonneſs, to put things in practice, which nothing but the utmoſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity can juſtifie; I conceive I ſhall effectually anſwer all that can be materially objected from <hi>the Caſe of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>the Defence of it,</hi> againſt our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Settlement, if I can maintain this Propoſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29442:5"/> That <hi>where a King is in the full and quiet poſſeſſion of the Throne, and Exerciſe of the Government; has been ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proclaimed, and freely and voluntarily recognized and ſubmitted unto by the States of the Kingdom as their King; has viſibly the Power and Strength of the Nation in his hands; the Laws have their due courſe in his Name, and all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick juſtice is adminiſtred by thoſe deputed and commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by him; altho he had no precedent legal Right, and that there is another perſon living, who according to the ordinary courſe of Hereditary Succeſſion, has a juſt claim to the Crown; yet the Laws of</hi> England <hi>do require every private ſubject to pay their Allegiance to ſuch a King in poſſeſſion, and protect them in their ſo doing.</hi> And this, I hope, will be fully made out, by plain Law, and all the ſeeming Objections offered againſt it from the Laws of the Land, anſwered.</p>
            <p>To ſave my ſelf and the Reader ſome trouble here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, it will be convenient, before I enter into the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular conſideration of our Author's Arguments and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, to obſerve, That the Government of <hi>England</hi> is to be conſidered in two reſpects: <hi>1ſt,</hi> With regard to the Power of Legiſlature, <hi>viz.</hi> The King and Body of the States, who have power over all poſitive Laws, to make new ones according as they in their Judgments ſhall think expedient, and to alter, amend, and ſupply the defects of the old ones, as they in prudence ſhall judg the preſent circumſtances of Affairs require. <hi>2ly,</hi> The Executive Power, of which the King is ſupreme, and Courts of Juſtice, and other Officers ſubordinate under him. To them it belongs not to deliberate or determine, what in their opinions it were fit or reaſonable the Law ſhould be, and thereupon declare that to be Law; but to declare what the Law is, as it at preſent ſtands, in every caſe coming judicially before them, and to put that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29442:5"/> Law in Execution. This is ſo very obvious, that it muſt without heſitation be agreed to me; and ſo muſt the conſequence that I draw from it: That I need not make it any part of the preſent Queſtion, Whether the Acts of one who is called an Uſurper in Title, that tend immediately to the deſtruction of the right of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed Prince, be juſt in themſelves, ſo that they ought to continue in force, and not be repealed and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled, by a Power competent for that purpoſe, upon the injured Prince's happening to be reſtored to his Right: But whether ſuch Acts being done according to the known legal Forms and Ceremonies, by ſuch a Poſſeſſor of the Throne as I have before deſcribed, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry private ſubject may not, in good Conſcience, ſubmit unto and obey them, without taking upon him to judge of his Governour's Title? Nay further, whether the Laws of the Land do not protect him in ſo doing; and not only ſo, but require it from him?</p>
            <p>I think the Affirmative is agreeable to the Laws: And I now come to conſider what our Author ſays to the contrary.</p>
            <p>The firſt Point he endeavours to make out, is, That notwithſtanding the Opinions of the Eminent Lawyers whom he mentions (which I muſt obſerve were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the times of Kings, whoſe Titles to the Crown were undoubted, ſo that there was no neceſſity for their ſtraining the ſenſe of the Law to make it favour their Maſter's intereſt: and which, for ought that ever yet has appeared, were never contradicted hitherto by any one of that profeſſion), <hi>A King de facto is not Seignior le Roy within the Statute of</hi> 25 E. 3.</p>
            <p>I ſhall through this Diſcourſe take thoſe words to mean, one who is in the full and peaceable poſſeſſion of the Throne, and Exerciſe of the Government, with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29442:6"/> the free ſubmiſſion of the People, by their Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives aſſembled in a Parliamentary way; but wants a Title by proximity of Blood and Hereditary Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and undertake for the defence of the duty of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to ſuch an one only, and not to any poſſeſſion without a true Right, ſhort of that: If any of the proofs which I ſhall make uſe of hereafter, ſhall carry it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they will more ſtrongly prove this: But I will not anſwer for more.</p>
            <p>I obſerve in general upon this Statute, 1. That the puniſhment preſcribed by it, for the offences now under debate, is the utmoſt to which a temporal Law can reach, <hi>Death and Diſgrace:</hi> This will make it highly reaſonable, that the offence ſhould be plain and certain. And in the ſecond place, That this Statute was made in favour of the Subject, that he might be at a certainty what hazards he runs, and not be ſwallowed up in the Gulf, before he apprehended himſelf to be beyond his Banks: It made no new offence, but was reſtrictive of the liberty that Judges had taken before, of expounding every thing, that an angry or jealous Prince did reſent as a wound of his Majeſty, into High Treaſon. This is ſo well known to all that have lookt into the Law, that it were idle to quote Authorities for it. I will, add in the third place, as a thing not improper to be obſerved, That it would be a very hard thing before <hi>E.</hi> 3's time to prove a certain Hereditary Succeſſion. The beſt Hiſtorian will find but few Inſtances of that kind from the Conqueſt till the time of the making of this Statute. So that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Hereditary Title, could not be a thing forgotten, or ſlipt over, as out of the minds of King or People: Yet I can't perceive any thing in this Statute, to lead to ſuch a diſtinction as is now made; tho it was made as a Rule for the Subject, from which he might learn, how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29442:6"/> he might demean himſelf in thoſe great matters with ſafety<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There is not ſo much as an Hint, that the trying who has the juſt Right and Title to the Crown, whether He, who is owned by the States of the Kingdom, and has the full Government and adminiſtration of all Affairs; or another, who a thoughtful buſie man (that can't con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelf in the private ſtation wherein God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty has placed him, but muſt <hi>make himſelf</hi> a Judge of the higheſt matters) will be fancying ought to be there. I ſay, That the trying that Point, ſhould be left to a Jury of 12 men; as it muſt be, ſhould a private perſon be proceeded againſt for an attempt upon the Poſſeſſor, in order to the reſtoring the diſpoſſeſſed Prince; If it be true, that it is not Treaſon by that Law, for a private Subject to attempt any thing againſt the King in poſſeſſion, in behalf of him, that of Right, by Hereditary Succeſſion, ought to be King.</p>
            <p>This would be an hard Interpretation of a Statute, made in the time of a King who obtained poſſeſſion of the Kingdom by a War levied againſt his Father, and a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Reſignation, after the Arms, of thoſe who took part with him, were ſucceſsful: In which taking up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King in poſſeſſion, notwithſtanding all that might juſtifie it in Reaſon of State and Prudence, he was ſenſible that the Laws of the Land would not bear his friends out; and therefore thought fit, in the firſt year of his Reign, to have an Act of Parliament paſſed, to indemnifie them againſt ordinary legal proceedings; for what they had done. This he lookt upon as neceſſary, tho at the ſame time, he thought the Cauſe in which thoſe who fell in the War, died, ſo juſt in it ſelf, that he made a new Law on purpoſe, to ſave them from ſuffering in their Eſtates: For we find, in the ſame year, there was a Statute made, to entitle the Executors of thoſe, who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29442:7"/> were Slain in his Quarrel, in the purſuit againſt his Father, to Actions to recover their Teſtators Goods.</p>
            <p>Lawyers account <hi>Co-temporaneam Expoſitionem,</hi> the beſt interpreter of the Senſe of Statute-laws. I would fain have the Author, or any one elſe, who would confine the words <hi>Seignior le Roy</hi> in that Statute, to, <hi>Lawful and Rightful King by Hereditary Succeſſion only,</hi> to ſhew any thing leading to that Interpretation in the Hiſtory of that time, or any of the Kings Reigns before that. Where it was ever heard of before that Act, that Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance was due to the uncrowned, unſubmitted-unto Right Heir? Nay, I will go farther, Where in any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Record, before that Statute, there does appear a damning of the Title of ſuch a King, after a Submiſſion of the People to him, in favour of him that was nearer in Blood? Whether the ſeveral Predeceſſors of <hi>E.</hi> 3. who had not a legal Title by Hereditary Succeſſion, are not called Kings, in the Statutes of almoſt every year of his Reign, and all their Acts unqueſtioned? If there were nothing extant to direct the Subjects to the contrary, and the King himſelf ſo often told them, that thoſe, whom <hi>I</hi> muſt call Kings <hi>de Facto</hi> only, were Kings without any addition (the very letter of this Statute) it would inſtead of being an Eaſe and Relief to the People, have proved according to the preſent Interpretation, the greateſt Snare that was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <p>'Twas eaſy for them to ſee and know who exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed the Kingly Office, under whoſe Adminiſtration they had the benefit of the Laws, and by whoſe Authority all Judicial Proceedings took their Courſe. They might too, without any great difficulty, learn who were the viſible Attendants on the Throne, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29442:7"/> King's near Relations, his Wife, Son, and Daughter. The Throne is but one, and they ſaw who poſſeſſed that. The name <hi>King,</hi> is a name of Office, which conſiſts in Exerciſe, that too was as plain to them. The words of the Statute ſeem as plain, <hi>'Tis Treaſon to compaſs or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the Death,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the King:</hi> Would it not now be a very great hardſhip to put it upon a private Perſon, to ſeek an hidden Senſe in plain Words, and at the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of his Life and Family, to make himſelf judge of all the Difficulties which may ariſe upon our Conſtitution, (which, what it is in all points, never was or will be agreed upon)? Whether this Perſon that is ſo expreſly within the words of the Statute, may not hereafter appear to have been wrongfully poſſeſſed: And upon that apprehenſion, to put the poor Man under an Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of laying himſelf, for the ſake of a Nation, open to the Vengeance of one, who has the plain words of the Law on his ſide, and Power to back it? To put him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a neceſſity of being a Sacrifice to his own private Opinion, againſt the publick acknowledgement of the Body of the People, in a caſe wherein common Senſe, and the Wiſdom of all Governments forbid the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a private Perſon to be a Judge; nay, won't en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure its being made the Subject of a nice and curious Inquiry?</p>
            <p>But I perceive by <hi>Defence</hi> f. 6, 7. That it is one main ground of our Author's Opinion, and whereon he prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally relies, That the Law does not look upon the King <hi>de Facto</hi> to be <hi>King,</hi> but accounts him that is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed, and <hi>de Jure</hi> ought to be ſo, to be ſo; and he calls upon Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> for Authorities to prove the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. This explains the two firſt Lines of his Book, where he makes it the deſcription of a King <hi>de Jure,</hi> That he is <hi>the Perſon that has the Regal Authority.</hi> The Doctor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29442:8"/> had aſſerted, That the King <hi>de Facto</hi> was King, as a ſelf-evident Propoſition; and I ſhould think my ſelf very ſafe in my Propoſition ſtill, were I in the Doctor's caſe, without any other proof. But <hi>I</hi> will for once comply with the Author's Requeſt, and refer him to a very ingenious Book, called, <hi>The Caſe of Allegiance to a King in Poſſeſſion,</hi> where he may find a great many unanſwerable Authorities to that purpoſe; e'en as many as ever there were Revocations, or Repeals of the Acts of ſuch Kings. There they declare, That the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> was in fact King, but not in right; and after they have done ſo, unleſs there can be two Kings, they have left no other ſenſe for the words, <hi>King de Jure,</hi> but that of right he ought to have been King all that time, tho the other in fact was ſo. For his full ſatisfaction, I will give him a taſte of one, out of many, and it ſhall be his <hi>Darling</hi> Act, the Statute 1 <hi>E.</hi> 4. which may be ſeen printed in the Record of <hi>Baggot</hi>'s Caſe, in the Year-book, 9 <hi>E.</hi> 4, 9, 10. The Author quotes it often, and once as an Authority for him in this point, becauſe (ſpeaking Hiſtorically, and deſcribing Perſons accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſeries of times, that it ſpeaks of them in) it calls <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>Henry</hi> late Earl of <hi>Darby,</hi> as he was, when he <hi>reared the War againſt</hi> R. 2. which is the thing that follows that Name: But let us ſee what other ill things it ſays of him, Why, <hi>He uſurped and intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the Royal Power, Eſtate, Dignity, Preheminence, Poſſeſſion, and Lordſhip of</hi> England. And after he had done ſo, and King <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. was dead, it is true, <hi>By Law, Cuſtom, and Conſcience, the Right and Title of the ſaid Crown and Lordſhip, deſcended to the Earl of</hi> March. But then (as if it were afraid the ſenſe of the words, <hi>Right and Title,</hi> ſhould be miſtaken) it ſets them in the next Sentence, in a direct Oppoſition to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29442:8"/> the Poſſeſſion of the Throne in the Senſe I contend for; where it ſays, That <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>according to the Right and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the ſaid Crown and Lordſhip, after the deceaſe of the Duke of</hi> York <hi>his Father, took upon him to uſe his Right and Title to the ſaid Realm, and enter'd into the Exerciſe of the Royal Eſtate, Dignity, Preheminence, and Power of the ſame Crown, and to the Reign and Governance of the ſaid Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and Lordſhip. And amoved</hi> H. 6. <hi>from the Occupation, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, Intruſion, Reign, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance of the ſaid Realm, to the great Joy of the Subject for their being departed from the Obeyſance and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the unrighteous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> &amp;c. If this be not enough, take the words more plainly, where the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute tells us, <hi>The Crown after the death of</hi> Rich. 2. ſhould <hi>have deſcended to the Earl of</hi> March, <hi>as next Heir of the Blood, if the ſaid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation had not been committed.</hi> The effect of theſe words is again repeated with regard to <hi>E.</hi> the <hi>4th</hi>'s Title. And the Statute expreſly diſtinguiſhes, <hi>That the King was in right from the death of his Father, very juſt King of the ſame Realm, but only from the fourth day of</hi> March, <hi>in lawful Poſſeſſion of the ſame Realm, with the Royal Power, Preheminence, Eſtate, and Dignity belonging to the Crown thereof;</hi> with abundance more to the ſame purpoſe. Theſe Authorities, without remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on them, will probably go a great way in proof of the Doctor's Propoſition; and the rather, becauſe they are of times when <hi>de Jure</hi> was triumphant; if they don't ſatisfy, upon a little Intimation, more ſhall be given.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, I can ſcarce with Patience hear ſome Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions that are fondly broached upon ſo weak a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation as a private Judgment; ſo very dangerous to all Governments, and deſtructive to the Perſons them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves who advance them. If the Conſtitution of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29442:9"/> Kingdom were plain and poſitive, ſo that it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any unbiaſſed, conſidering Man, to think otherwiſe, but that our Monarchy is ſo <hi>unalterably</hi> Hereditary, that neither the Conſent, or other Act, nor any manifeſt impediment or defect of the Perſon, who is next in Blood, could according to our Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deveſt him of his Right to the Crown, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Subject from Obedience to him; Then, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, a private Man, whoſe certain knowledg of the Royal Pedegree convinced him where the undoubted Right was, might reaſonably think himſelf bound in Juſtice and Conſcience to purſue that Title with his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, however Unſucceſsful, Violence, and Injuſtice might for ſome time render the Undertaking. But ſince it muſt be agreed, That the Hereditary Right to the Crown by our Conſtitution, was never lookt upon to be ſo ſacred and inviolable, but that the next in Courſe may have ſuch a known unfitneſs and incapacity upon him, of anſwering any of the ends of Government, that he may, without any Violation of that Conſtitution, be laid aſide: (As ſuppoſe him, to inſtance in one that all Mankind agree in, a perfect Ideot from his Nativity) And that one, who was once poſſeſſed of the Crown, may deveſt himſelf of his Right of Government, by a voluntary Quitting, or Reſignation of it; which may be done without making the whole Nation witneſſes to it. So that it muſt be allowed, that there may be inſtances wherein proximity of Blood in the right Line, will not be an infallible Badge of a Right to govern; and there may be great doubts who has the beſt Title. And ſince in the Caſe of an abſolute Incapacity to Rule, and in differences and competition between Titles, there muſt be ſome Judge. And ſince <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage</hi> ſay, That things of that nature, ought not to be of any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29442:9"/> Determination, but are proper for the Deciſion of thoſe who repreſent the whole Body of the People only, the whole being concerned in it; I can't tell whether Pity, or an hard Name will beſt ſuit that particular Member of the Body, who will not acquieſce in the Deciſion which the States of the Kingdom (his own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives amongſt the reſt) make of ſuch a Caſe; but muſt be ſetting up particular Notions of his own, and taking a great deal of Pains to warp, and with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſtrain the plain words of a Law to his own undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. If thoſe who argue ſo warmly againſt themſelves, and every private Subject of <hi>England</hi> in this matter, would but conſider what is ſaid before, that the 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. was made in favour of the Subject, to ſhew him his danger before he fell into it, and that it was not at all the end of that Law, to ſettle the Right of the Crown, (which our Author agrees is done by the Fundamental Conſtitution, and not any poſitive written Law) but only to ſecure the Peace and Quiet of the Kingdom from the attempts of private Perſons againſt their Governors, That the deſcription the Law generally gives of Treaſon, is, that 'tis <hi>Crimen Laeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> which ſeems to refer principally to the Office, and the Perſon as inveſtd with that, not to a diſpoſſeſſed, tho rightful Heir, who is forced into a private Condition, and has little of that Majeſty to be guarded: And that in <hi>Glanvill</hi>'s time, the Peace and Settlement of the Kingdom was ſo much conſidered, that it was called Treaſon, <hi>Machinari Sedition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Regni,</hi> as well as <hi>Mortem Regis;</hi> They would ſurely confine their thoughts to their Cloſets, till they could ſhew a little better Agreement between them, and what has been the received Opinion in all Ages, ſince the making of the Statute; or till they can write enough to ſatisfy a prudent Man, that it were to be wiſhed it were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29442:10"/> The doing which, I preſume, will take ſome time; ſince I could never yet meet with <hi>One,</hi> till I ſaw the contrary in Print, who did not think it ſo reaſonable in it ſelf, and ſo much the common concern of Mankind to maintain it; that 'twas their Senſe, words ought to be ſtrained (if there were need of it) to ſupport, not to deſtroy the Propoſition I am endeavouring to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
            <p>The Author allows ſome of thoſe particular Treaſons recited in the Act, <hi>As the Clipping the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper's Coin,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſe,</hi> f. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Counterfeiting his Seal, nay, Levying War againſt him upon any account, but in behalf of the diſpoſſeſſed Prince; may by the Law</hi> (that is by this Law, for there is none other for it) <hi>be puniſhed as Treaſon.</hi> He is very cautious indeed in his wording of it; <hi>Theſe may be Treaſon under an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> and puniſhed as Treaſon <hi>under</hi> an Uſurper: And will not confeſs in expreſs words, That theſe are Treaſons <hi>againſt</hi> him, but that they are rather <hi>againſt the courſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the Authority of the Lawful King through him.</hi> The notion is fine, but 'tis of very late date; the Indictments upon which thoſe Perſons are to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſpeak nothing of it; they ſay, <hi>'Tis againſt the Duty of their Allegiance to him, and againſt his Crown and Dignity.</hi> And it will be hard to make the word <hi>King</hi> in one part of the Statute, ſignify only a certain Perſon, who ought of Right to be King, but is not ſo, and perhaps never may; when the ſame word, without any Explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtands in the next line for <hi>another</hi> Perſon poſſeſſed of the Throne by wrong, and in prejudice of the Man's right that was deſcribed by the ſelf-ſame word juſt before.</p>
            <p>When the Author convincingly proves, That the next of the Royal Line in courſe of deſcent, has as inherent and inſeperable a Right to the Allegiance of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29442:10"/> as God Almighty has to the Worſhip and Service of his Creatures; and that <hi>an Idol in Poſſeſſion,</hi> as he words it, by virtue of its being ſet up in a Temple, is poſſeſſed of God's Power, and God Almighty deveſted of all Rule, (not to run the Parallel farther for fear of Blaſphemy) then I will grant he has offered a good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prove that the word <hi>King</hi> in this Statute <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſe,</hi> f. 7. <hi>Defen.</hi> f. 4.</note> can <hi>only</hi> ſignify the <hi>Right Heir,</hi> by the ſame Reaſon that the word <hi>God</hi> in the third Commandment can mean none but the <hi>True God.</hi> The Being of God is in its Nature unchangeable, his Name, and Right to govern us incommunicable. The Office of a King, and the Right of particular Perſons to that Office, are of politick Inſtitution, and may be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. It may often vary, and ceaſe, either for a time, or abſolutely, according to the Laws of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
            <p>So if the Author will make the Prieſthood ſuch an Office, as, that a Man's exerciſing the Functions of it will make him really and in truth a Prieſt, without entring in at the door (which my Profeſſion does not lead me to the Interpretation of; but I ſuppoſe the Author muſt think, ſignifies ſome ſetting apart, by thoſe with whom Chriſt has left ſuch a Power) then his Text may bear ſome Reſemblance to an Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into an Office, of which all ſides agree Poſſeſſion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Defen.</hi> f. 4.</note> may be taken by force, and that that Poſſeſſion does make him in fact (tho not in Right and Juſtice) a King.</p>
            <p>I could have wiſhed, that our Author had conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little better, before he had made theſe and ſome <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Def.</hi> f. 69.</note> other Compariſons.</p>
            <p>Our Author will make me weary of putting him in mind what the end of the Statute 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. was; if
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29442:11"/> he had weighed that well, he would have found, That notwithſtanding what is offered by him, from the word <hi>Heir,</hi> againſt the Interpretation, my <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſe</hi> f. 7. <hi>Def.</hi> f. 8.</note> Lord <hi>Coke</hi> was not ſo much in the wrong, when he ſaid, That <hi>our Lord the King,</hi> meant him that <hi>is King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already ſaid, That that Statute does not offer any thing towards the Determination of the Title to the Crown; who ought to be King, whether he that is in Poſſeſſion, or another who pretends he has a juſt Claim to it, is not its buſineſs. There is, notwithſtanding what our Author ſays to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, another proper place for the deciding ſuch a Controverſy. But the Law declared by this Statute, ſecures the Throne againſt the Attempts of private Subjects, and binds them to a quiet Submiſſion to the Office and Power, which is ſacred, in whoſe hands ſoever it is And therefore (taking our Monarchy to be an Hereditary one, as it undoubtedly is) I can ſee nothing <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> much leſs <hi>contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious</hi> in the affirming, That the Eldeſt Son of a King <hi>de Facto,</hi> that is, one owned and ſubmitted unto by the People as their King, is Heir apparent to the Crown, and ought to be looked upon as ſuch, by every private Subject, until the Rightful Owner regain the Poſſeſſion, or obtain the Sentence of thoſe, to whom the Right of determining it belongs, in his favour.</p>
            <p>Poſſeſſion, without any precedent Title, is a good Title againſt all the World, but him that has the true Right; ſo that, as between the Uſurper and any private Perſon, the Uſurper has a Right to the Throne, which is by the Conſtitution an Hereditary one. The Author himſelf will grant this, unleſs ſuch
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29442:11"/> private perſon act in behalf of him, whom he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to have the very Right; but of that Right, I cannot by any means allow the private Subject a Judge.</p>
            <p>I will readily agree, That this Statute did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any kindneſs to the Uſurper, or the eſtabliſhment of his Title: nay, that the principal aim and deſign of the Law (of which that Statute was declaratory) was to preſerve the Government, by ſecuring the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the King, (a Poſſeſſion and Right then going to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) and taking care of the Succeſſion. And it has taken a much more effectual way to do it, then our Author's Interpretation, if that were admitted, would do. Let us turn our Author's Expoſition into expreſs words, and the Law will run thus, <hi>It ſhall be High Treaſon to compaſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Death of the Lawful and Rightful King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But if there be one in Poſſeſſion of the Throne, who is not Lawful and Rightful King, then it ſhall be no fault for any particular Subject to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>his Death, in order to the inſtating him that has Right, in the Throne.</hi> Would ever any King, be his Title never ſo undoubted, think himſelf advantaged or ſecured by ſuch a Proviſion, where, by expreſs words of a Law, liberty would be given to every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Subject, to examine and paſs Sentence on his Right? Is it not a more reaſonable and prudent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and more likely, even to prevent an Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in after times, to guard by expreſs Law his Perſon, (who was at the time of the making the Law rightful Poſſeſſor) and that of him, who of Right ought to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him, and ſo downwards for ever under the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Penalties. And (taking it for granted, that that Proviſion would keep the Right and Poſſeſſion toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to require the Obedience of every particular
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29442:12"/> Subject to the Poſſeſſor from time to time, without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Rabble a liberty of examining into the Title.</p>
            <p>So that it is very far from being an unreaſonable Expoſition of the Law, tho it ſhould happen to be a Protection to the Wife and Son of an Uſurper in Title, to ſay the Title of the Poſſeſſor of the Crown ſhall not be canvaſſed by every Subject, but the Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Office ſhall ſet him above any particular perſons paſſing <hi>Sentence</hi> on, and exerciſing <hi>Authority</hi> over him.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, The Common-Law, which made ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Proviſion for the ſecurity of the Perſons of the King and his Relations, could not do it for any Sanctity of their Perſons, any otherwiſe, than as they were inveſted with the Kingly Office, and in relation to that. It ſecured them for their own ſakes, but more for the ſake of the Government, and to preſerve the Peace and Order of that. It ſuppoſed indeed, that no Perſon would obtain <hi>it,</hi> but he who had a Right, becauſe no other ought to do ſo; and all the Subjects are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged under the greateſt ties to prevent it; But 'twas as far from the Intention of the Law, as it is from Senſe and Reaſon, to leave it at the liberty, nay, make it the duty of every particular perſon to raiſe Diſturbances, and throw an whole Kingdom into Confuſion; becauſe he, againſt the Recognition and Senſe of the Body of the People, thinks another's Title to the Crown better than his who wears it. So, (to carry this on) as againſt the People who have no Right at all to the Crown, for the preſerving and continuing the Hereditary Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, it provided for and ſecured the Son of the King in Poſſeſſion, as the Perſon who according to our Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, has preſumptively a Right to ſucceed his Father
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29442:12"/> in the Throne, till there be ſome Authoritative Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration againſt his Father's Title. I confeſs, <hi>Heir Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to a King</hi> de facto, <hi>who has no Title to the Crown, but his own Poſſeſſion,</hi> as the Author has tacked the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Def.</hi> f. 9.</note> words together, does ſeem odd; but the difficulty is in the words only, not in the thing. The name King is never clogged with theſe words <hi>de Facto,</hi> till he is out of Poſſeſſion: The private Subject muſt look upon him as his King, and conſequently on his Son, as the Heir of his King, and ſo not attempt any thing againſt them, which is what the Laws againſt Treaſon provide for. The <hi>de Facto,</hi> which is all that imports any inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or Contradiction, does not then belong to him.</p>
            <p>But we are told, <hi>That the conſtant Practice and Cuſtom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſe</hi> f. 9. <hi>Def.</hi> f. 13.</note> 
               <hi>of the Realm, is ſo far from warranting my Lord</hi> Coke<hi>'s Gloſs, that it proves the contrary. For that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon every Revolution, uſed to Attaint the Adherents to thoſe who oppoſed them, tho acting under a King in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; nay, dealt with the Poſſeſſor himſelf as a Traytor, ſcarce allowed him the Name of a King, or lookt upon his Acts of Government as Valid and Authoritative in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I lay all theſe together, becauſe the ſame Anſwer will in a great meaſure ſerve for all of them, tho each may have its particular conſideration.</p>
            <p>None of thoſe Proceedings amount to ſo much as a colourable Proof, That to act againſt one, who in Juſtice, and according to our Conſtitution ought to be King, but is out of Poſſeſſion; in Obedience unto, and Defence of the King who is publickly ſubmitted unto by the Body of the Kingdom, and in Poſſeſſion of the Government, is by any Law, at preſent a Law of the Land, Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. All thoſe Attainders were by Parliaments, whoſe Power is not to be contradicted, or the Reaſons of their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29442:13"/> Proceedings diſputed: It was, without doubt, by all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate men at that time lookt upon as very hard, and contrary to Equity, to puniſh men by poſitive Laws, <hi>ex poſt facto,</hi> for what was no breach of any of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Laws, or Acts of State then in being. Theſe Laws were undoubtedly <hi>iniquae,</hi> unequitable, but I believe no one would have put the Author to the trouble of <hi>proving them to be Laws.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Def.</hi> f. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The People either of themſelves to make Court to the Power then uppermoſt, or being over-awed by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Recommendation of thoſe about the King, did generally elect and return the Friends and Adherents of the prevailing Party, whoſe Wounds being freſh, and their Loſſes quick and piercing, they kept themſelves within no bounds of Juſtice or Moderation: They were reſolved to gratify their private Reſentments, and revenge themſelves for Injuries done them or their Friends upon any terms; ſo that they took not either the Laws of the Land, or the common Rules of Juſtice, for their guide, but made both truckle to their Paſſions. The King was glad to leſſen the number of his Enemies, the cutting off many of whom, and frightning the reſt into Submiſſion by ſuch Examples of his Severity, he lookt upon as the only means to ſecure himſelf againſt another turn. That this was the Caſe, is certain, and I wiſh we could find in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in our Ancient Hiſtories <hi>only,</hi> in the times of our <hi>Edward</hi>'s and <hi>Henry</hi>'s, to prove, that where there are two conteſting Parties in a Kingdom, neither of them will make uſe of the advantages they happen to obtain over the other, with ſuch a temper as right Reaſon and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would direct. But the violence of ſuch Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings muſt not be offered as any proof or meaſure of Right; nay, they are unfit to be mentioned, or made uſe of in any cool debate, unleſs it be to create in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29442:13"/> minds of Men, an abhorrence of ſuch Actings, and by ſetting forth the calamitous Conſequences that were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the puniſhing the poor Subject, upon the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Succeſſes on cach ſide, to recommend that wiſe and equal Law, which not only declared, That the Subject <note place="margin">11 <hi>H.</hi> 7.</note> ought to be indemnified in his paying his Service to the King for the time being, for that it was his <hi>Duty</hi> to do ſo; but provided, That all Statutes made afterwards to the contrary, ſhould be void. This latter part was all of the Statute which was new, the reſidue was always Law, and is there only authoritatively declared to be ſo. And that part of it that was new, can't have its full effect to reſtrain ſubſequent Parliaments, to which no poſitive Laws can give bounds. But yet their aiming at ſuch a Reſtraint, is a ſufficient Caution to future Parliaments, to conſider very well before they make any Law contrary to it; which is thereby adjudged a thing utterly unfit to be done, and that in the moſt ſolemn manner, by as wiſe a Prince as ever filled the Throne; and a People, whoſe Sufferings under the miſchiefs of a contrary Practice had convinced them, not only of the reaſonableneſs, but the abſolute neceſſity of the thing.</p>
            <p>I think, I need not ſay any thing farther as to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances out of Hiſtory, during the Wars between <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> If there were need, the Author has done it to my hand, <hi>Caſe</hi> f. 11. and elſewhere; at leaſt, as to any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Right or Juſtice that can be drawn from the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance they dealt to each other upon any Advantages. <hi>E.</hi> 4. attainted <hi>H.</hi> 6. and all his Adherents, being an Uſurper upon his Rights, and gave very hard words to him, as well as to his Grand-father <hi>H.</hi> 4. the firſt Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Right of the Houſe of <hi>York;</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 6. his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing actually a King in Poſſeſſion was not a Protection againſt it. Will it thence follow, that by the ſtanding
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29442:14"/> Law of <hi>England,</hi> a King in Poſſeſſion not being rightful Heir to the Crown, and all thoſe that act under him, are Traytors and Rebels to the diſpoſſeſſed Prince? Will not <hi>H.</hi> 6th returning his Complement to the full, when he was reſtored to the Crown, as effectually prove the Law to be with him being in Poſſeſſion, tho <hi>E.</hi> 4. had the better Title. In truth, none of theſe Inſtances prove any thing, but that <hi>de Facto</hi> and <hi>de Jure</hi> were much alike eſteemed, when they got the Power into their hands; they made their Parliaments ſay, and do what they pleaſed, when either of them had ſufficient Power to put the Acts made againſt his Rival, and thoſe who adhered to him, in Execution.</p>
            <p>I can't forbear obſerving, That in all theſe <hi>violent</hi> times, there is not ſo much as one Inſtance of any Perſon adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Traytor for his ſerving the King in Poſſeſſion, upon an Indictment in the ordinary courſe of proceedings accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the eſtabliſht Laws. All thoſe Determinations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the Parliament, <hi>ex plenitudine poteſtatis.</hi> And 'tis plain, that they did not ſo much as pretend to ſquare their Actions to the Laws then in being, by the Inſtance he gives, where <hi>H.</hi> 6. is attainted of High Treaſon for <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſe</hi> f. 10.</note> the death of <hi>Richard</hi> D. of <hi>York</hi> at the Battel of <hi>Wakefield,</hi> when 'tis apparent, not only that the D. of <hi>York</hi> had by his own Agreement and Oath put himſelf into the condition of a Subject to <hi>H.</hi> 6. during his Life; but that the poor King was at the time of the fighting that Battel, in the Power of the D. of <hi>York</hi> himſelf, left by him in the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody of the D. of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and E. of <hi>Warwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not to mention that the Author agrees, the D. of <hi>York</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſe</hi> f. 11.</note> was not King, but only declared Heir to the Crown after <hi>H.</hi> 6th's death. And all agree, That the death of the Heir <note place="margin">3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 9.</note> Collateral to the Crown, is not High Treaſon within 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29442:14"/>
            <p> As to his particular inſtances of hard Names given by <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. to the <hi>pretended Parliament</hi> 49 <hi>H.</hi> 6. beſides what has been obſerved in general before, I will add only, that the Right and Juſtice of his Cauſe depended upon the Nullity of their Proceedings; and yet he durſt not inſiſt upon the Original Nullity of them, which (it may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed he knew) 'twas not the part of private Men or the Judges to determine: And therefore it was done by a Law; and that Law is an Act of Repeal only, <hi>Reverſing, revoking,</hi> and <hi>making,</hi> not <hi>declaring</hi> the former proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings void.</p>
            <p>Nor is there any thing in what we find <hi>Caſe. f.</hi> 14. that can amount to a Proof of his Poſition. In the end of that Page he grants that Acts of Parliament paſſed under an Uſurper are valid without any Confirmation: If he had not, we have a better Authority for it, That of the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame Parliament that gave the Determination in favour of the <hi>D. of Tork</hi>'s Title to the Crown: <hi>That the Laws took no place againſt that.</hi> And they that were ſo bold to do that, would not have been afraid to have carried it on further, if Law or Reaſon would have ſuffered them. Yet they, and the <hi>D. of York</hi> himſelf, ſolemnly declare, <hi>That all the other Acts and Ordinances made in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper's Parliament, be good and ſufficient.</hi> (Now if it be eſſential to every Act of Parliament, that the King's Approbation give it life, ſurely the Law muſt look upon thoſe Perſons to have been <hi>Seigniors les Roys,</hi> whoſe Laws are unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably allowed to be good.) Nay, it appears moſt plainly that the Statute of 1 <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. for confirmation of Judicial proceedings, which our Author inſiſts on, was <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 14. Def. <hi>f.</hi> 37.</note> Cautionary only, and that from the Act it ſelf; for the Preamble ſays, 'twas made, <hi>In eſchewing of Ambiguities, Doubts, and Diverſities of Opinions which may ariſe, enſue, and be taken,</hi> &amp;c. when he was ſetled in the Throne, and the Parliament and Judges (as 'twill be eaſily believed) were
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29442:15"/> ready to complement his Right to the higheſt pitch; they could not ſtrain it higher, than to make it a <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> caſe, whether the Acts of the preceding <hi>Kings in Deed, not in Right,</hi> were not valid. And the words uſed in the Statute are <hi>Declare, Eſtabliſh, and Enact, &amp;c.</hi> the firſt of which, we know, was never lookt upon as a proper word for introducing a new Law; or made uſe of upon ſuch an occaſion.</p>
            <p>But his third Argument deſerves ſomething a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f</hi> 11. Def. <hi>f.</hi> 32.</note> conſideration. <hi>It is this: If Treaſon lay only againſt the King in Poſſeſſion, whether King</hi> de jure <hi>or no, then the Subjects may not, under pain of High Treaſon, admit any Claim of the King</hi> de jure <hi>againſt him; for that were to be adherent to the Enemy of the King in poſſeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs I wonder that a Man of our Author's Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Reaſon ſhould ſet down ſuch a Conſequence: But this was brought in, 'tis probable, to make way for the main Aſſertion of his Book, and the moſt material thing in the whole Controverſie, <hi>That the Parliament cannot</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 65.</note> 
               <hi>be, and that there is no Judicature provided to determine the Title to the Crown, where there is a Competition about it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both theſe will receive one Anſwer. I ſhould think (if there were no Precedent or Expreſs Authority in the point) that it would be allowed a ſufficient proof of the contrary, That Right Reaſon, and the very Nature of Government, do make ſome ſuch power of determining abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. For the Foundation of all Governments is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be the good and benefit of thoſe who form themſelves into it; and in all caſes whatſoever, unleſs there be an expreſs proviſion to the contrary, what is agreeable to the Senſe and Reaſon of Mankind, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the ſupport and well-being of that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, muſt be ſuppoſed to be the very firſt general ground agreed upon: ſo that in ſuch caſes, where there is not any thing poſitive againſt it, <hi>Is</hi> and <hi>ought to be,</hi> ſeem in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29442:15"/> reaſon to be covertible terms. And <hi>2dly,</hi> There cannot, as the frame of our Conſtitution is, any other be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, than the States of the Kingdom. This I am ſure will be agreed unto me, If there be any ſuch Judicature, it can be none but they: And allowing them to be ſo, common ſenſe will ſay, They being made Judges, muſt thereby <hi>impliedly</hi> have a Right to act in it, free from all precedent Obligations of Duty to either Party; They act as freely in that point, till the Determination is made, as their Anceſtors did, when they may be ſuppoſed to be met together, to agree upon a Form of Government; Only that they are to keep to the Rule, which they find ſetled and agreed on both ſides, <hi>viz.</hi> That our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is an Hereditary Monarchy; And the Queſtion to be determined by them is, Which of the Pretenders has the beſt Title upon that Foundation. Is it not then an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front put upon the judgment of a Reader, to ſay, That, becauſe it is maintained, that the poſitive Laws of the Land, for the Quiet and Preſervation of the Monarchy, forbid every private Subject, in his capacity of a Subject, to take upon him to cenſure the Title of a King poſſeſſed of the Throne, it will thence follow, That the States or Body of the Nation, when there is ſuch a ſtop in the proceedings, by ſome doubt upon the very Conſtitution it ſelf, that the whole is likely to fall, unleſs a deciſion be made of it; ſhall not have an equal Power to reſcue themſelves from that Confuſion, as their Anceſtors had to form themſelves into Order.</p>
            <p>They do this upon the Reaſon of the Conſtitution it ſelf, and by a Power and Fundamental Right, which of neceſſity muſt be ſuppoſed to be reſerved, when they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied themſelves into a Politick frame: they act in it upon their old Natural Liberty, which could never be ſubmitted to the Prince in this inſtance, becauſe the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ariſes only upon the doubt, who is the Prince.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29442:16"/>
            <p> And therefore the Duke of <hi>Tork,</hi> in his Anſwer to the Objection, that was made againſt his Claim to the Crown from the Oaths they had taken to <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. tells the Lords, <hi>He lawfully may claim and purſue his right, and demand Juſtice in ſuch form as he doth: And that all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and namely the Peers and Lords of this Realm may, and by Law of God and Man ought, to help and aſſiſt him in Truth and Juſtice, notwithſtanding thoſe Oaths,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Our Author calls for a proof, of the Authority of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament <note place="margin">Def. <hi>f.</hi> 34.</note> or States of the Kingdom, to determine the Rights of conteſting Princes: As if there were a printed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Fundamental Conſtitution extant, by which the Priviledges and Powers of each part of it are limited. 'Tis ſaid before, that neceſſity of Government warrants this; and the ſame neceſſity warrants their convening in order to it, without the formality of a Summons. That Form and Method of proceeding ſuppoſes a King and Government ſetled, and is one of the Rules which direct the King how he ſhall adminiſter that Government, and what are the Duties and Offices of particular perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it: This is above all thoſe Forms; a neceſſary Means to ſettle the Rule it ſelf.</p>
            <p>However, I am pretty confident that thoſe converſant in our ancient Hiſtories, and Parliamentary Records, will find reaſon, to carry the Power of the States of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom farther, rather than to deny their Authority in this point. The Claim of the D. of <hi>York</hi> 39 <hi>H.</hi> 6. is not the only inſtance of the thing; but it being a very ſolemn and notorious one, and a full proof of this point, I will lay it down a little more fully and in a piece, then it was for our Authors turn to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> 39 <hi>H.</hi> 6. comes to the Parliament, and <hi>by his Counſel,</hi> puts in his Claim in Writing, to the Crown; deriving his Pedigree very plainly, ſo as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title himſelf as next Heir by a Lineal Succeſſion.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29442:16"/>
            <p> The Pedigree could not be unknown, to any one of the Lords, before whom the claim was laid; yet King <hi>H.</hi> 6. having long enjoyed the Crown, the Lords ſay, <hi>The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſo high, and of ſuch weight, that it was not to any of the Subjects to enter into Communication thereof, without his high Commandment, Agreement and Conſent had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi> They thereupon go to the King opening the Claim; He could not be put into a better condition then he was; and therefore, had he lookt upon this cautiouſneſs of the Lords to be more than Complement, he would never have conſented to their hearing it; but he does not offer to forbid their proceeding; tho 'tis certain he was ſenſible of the defects of his Title, and therefore earneſtly prays the Lords to examine ſtrictly, and raiſe all the Objections they could againſt the Duke's Title.</p>
            <p>Then they read the Claim, and order the Judges to ſay what they could in maintenance of the King's Right. They excuſe themſelves, ſay, <hi>It hath not been accuſtomed to call the Juſtices to Counſel in ſuch matters; the matter was too high, and toucht the King's High Eſtate and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galie, which is above the Law, and paſſed their Learning; wherefore they durſt not enter into any Communication there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for it pertained to the Lords of the King's Blood and the apparage of this Land, to have Communication and meddle in ſuch matters.</hi> But this was not the only reaſon the Judges gave for their ſilence; They ſay, <hi>They were the King's Juſtices, and have to determine ſuch matters as come before them in the Law; between party and party they may not be of Counſel: And this matter was between the King and the ſaid Duke of</hi> York <hi>as two parties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Judges Excuſe was allowed as proper, for, Counſel was not their Duty; 'twas not a matter to be adjudged by the expreſs Laws of the Land, of which they had the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Execution; but by ſomething above the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Laws; And, they were not a part of the Parliament,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29442:17"/> that Power of determining they had none. But the King's Attorney and other Counſel being required to do what had been required of the Judges, the like Excuſe would not be admitted from them, <hi>for they were the King's par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Counſellers, and therefore they had their Fees and Wages:</hi> They return, <hi>They were the King's Counſellers in the Law, in ſuch things as were under his Authority, or by Commiſſion; but this matter was above his authority, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they might not meddle:</hi> Yet they are over-ruled, for 'twas their Duty to offer what they could in a Court of Judicature in defence of their Maſter's Title. Then <hi>It was agreed by all the Lords, that every Lord ſhould have his freedom to ſay what he could ſay, without any reporting or magre to be had for his trying.</hi> And <hi>after the ſaying of all the Lords, every after other,</hi> Objections are framed againſt the Duke's claim. The Duke puts in Anſwers to them, and often prays that the matter might be determined. The Lords ſolemnly declare that the Duke's Title could not be <hi>defeated,</hi> but agree upon the Expedient which the Chancellor propoſes, <hi>deſiring the Lords, that if any of them could find any other or better means, that it might be ſhewed; whereupon after ſad and ripe Communication in this matter had, it was concluded and agreed by all the ſaid Lords, that ſith is was ſo, that the Title of the ſaid Duke of</hi> York <hi>cannot be defeated, and in eſchewing the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience that might enſue, to take the means above re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed</hi> (viz. <hi>That the King ſhould keep the Crowns, and his Eſtate and Dignity Royal, during his life, and the ſaid Duke, and his Heirs, to ſucceed him in the ſame.)</hi> The Lords open this Expedient to the King, and both the Parties ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſubmit and agree to it.</p>
            <p>From this proceeding 'tis very plain in the firſt place (which I toucht upon before) That if the Judges who made the Excuſe, and Lords who admitted it, know any thing of our Conſtitution, they are to judge according to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29442:17"/> the known and written poſitive Laws of the Land, which preſcribe the Offices and Duties of particular perſons, and to ſpeak what their ſenſe is; but have nothing to do with enquiring into, or giving their Judgment upon the King's Title: They are to put the Laws in Execution under the King: But they can't find any Law to condemn or med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the Title of the King in poſſeſſion, no nor to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, (being called in queſtion in a proper place.) The Laws with which they were intruſted, meddle not with it the one way or the other; And they declared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves incompetent to give any Advice or Determination in it; tho our Author will make every particular man a competent Judge of it.</p>
            <p>And 'tis as plain in the next place, That all the Parties agree the Parliament to be proper Determiners of ſuch a difference, (which may inform our Author, who after e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting a Court in every private man's breaſt to do it, can't find in our Conſtitution any Court for that purpoſe.) Nay <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 66.</note> the Judges tell you, The King and the Duke are before them <hi>as party and party:</hi> That is, Two perſons, conteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a proper Court, for a Judicial Determination.</p>
            <p>The Lords think ſo too; They oblige the King's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to appear before them, and defend their Majeſties Right, as a part of the Service that they owe the King, <hi>for their Fees and Wages:</hi> The Duke often preſſes them for their Judgment, and at laſt they give it.</p>
            <p>In the third place, I obſerve that this Expedient is of the Lords own finding out, and they decree it. 'Tis true, in the Chancellors repeating the Opinion of the Lords, there are the words, <hi>If he would,</hi> upon which great ſtreſs is often laid, not only by our Author, but others; and more then the thing will juſtly bear: The Chancellor ſays, <hi>That it was thought by all the Lords that the Title of the ſaid Duke cannot be defeated:</hi> That is, That none of thoſe things objected to it, had deſtroyed the Right of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29442:18"/> Duke and his Line, for ever. <hi>And in eſchewing the great Inconvenience that may enſue, a mean was found to ſave the King's Honour and Eſtate, and to appeaſe the ſaid Duke if he would,</hi> &amp;c (which imports no more, then that the mean they agreed upon, would be to his ſatisfaction, if he would be contented with reaſonable terms) This, I ſay, is only the repetition of the Chancellor of the reſult of the Lords Debate: But when they come to the Judgment, that is general; That the ſaid mean ſhall be taken; and this given, before any Declaration of the Conſent either of the Duke or King to it; tho afterwards, upon its being opened to them, it was with great ſolemnity agreed unto by them, and paſſed by the King into an Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>The very Statute of 1 <hi>E.</hi> 4. allows this Judgment to be good; and that, by virtue of it, and the Agreement upon it, <hi>H.</hi> 6. ſhould. have held the Crown for his life, tho the very Right were with the D. of <hi>York:</hi> But it being part of the Agreement that the Lords ſhould ſupport it, <hi>and keep, obſerve and ſtrengthen, inaſmuch as appertaineth to them, all the ſaid things, and reſiſt to their power, all them that will preſume the contrary, according to their Eſtates and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. E.</hi> 4. gets a ſolemn Declaration by that Statute, that <hi>H.</hi> 6. had attempted the breaking the Agreement, and therefore his diſpoſſeſſing him was juſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He thought it adviſable, that the breach of the particular Agreement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Crown, as well as the Title it ſelf, ſhould be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſetled by Parliament: And indeed the very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all Acts of Recognition, and the conſtant uſage of them in almoſt every Reign, ſhew the Expediency of ſome publick Declaration to the People, that they may know to whom their Obedience is due; and imply as much as the Preamble of the Stat. 1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. ſpeaks in expreſs words, which Preamble our Author quotes, becauſe it affirms the Title of an Uſurper; (He was an Uſurper, but one who made as good and wiſe Laws, as any lawful King his Predeceſſor)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29442:18"/> 
               <hi>That the moſt part of the People can't be ſufficiently learned in the Laws and Cuſtoms which make out a Right and Title to the Crown: And that the Court of Parliament is of ſuch Authority, and the People of the Land of ſuch a Nature and Diſpoſition, that Manifeſtation or Declaration of any Truth made by the three Eſtates of the Realm aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by Authority of the ſame, makes, before all things moſt faithful and certain quieting of men's minds, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves the occaſions of Doubts and ſeditious Language.</hi> This is Truth and Reaſon out of whoſe mouth ſoever it comes, or for whatever End it was pronounced; and in all Juſtice ought to protect every private Perſon in his ſubmiſſion to a Power acknowledged in that manner, againſt all the Diſturbers of the quiet of our preſent Settlement.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider the Obſervations he makes upon the Authorities quoted by my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> to juſtifie the gloſs made upon the words <hi>Seigneour le Roy</hi> in the 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. The firſt is <hi>Baggot</hi>'s Caſe. To ſtate this matter fairly, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears on the Book, the Caſe in ſhort is this. <hi>Baggot</hi> brings an Aſſize of his Office, <hi>&amp;c. Ivie</hi> the Tenant pleads, <hi>Baggot</hi> was an Alien, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo could not hold the Office, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not being the King's Liege Subject. <hi>Baggot</hi> replies, his <note place="margin">9 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>b.</hi> 9 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 9.</note> Letters of <hi>Naturalization. Ivie</hi> ſets forth the Act 1 <hi>E.</hi> 4. which recites at large the Pedigree and Title of <hi>E.</hi> 4. and the Uſurpation of the three <hi>Henries,</hi> and averrs, that the Patent was granted by <hi>H.</hi> 6. one of the Uſurpers; and ſo leaves it to the Court to judge whether the Patent was valid in Law: <hi>Baggot</hi> demurrs upon this Rejoynder, and <hi>Ivie</hi> joyns in demurrer. <hi>Brian,</hi> of Counſel for <hi>Ivie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, <note place="margin">9 <hi>E</hi> 4. 11. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> That King <hi>E.</hi> 4. being reſtored in his Remitter, as Couſin and Heir of King <hi>R.</hi> 2. the Patent made by K. <hi>Henry,</hi> who was but an Uſurper and Intruder, was void, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I will not repeat what <hi>Baggot</hi>'s Councel offer, becauſe the greateſt part of it is mentioned by our Author, as well as my Lord <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 16. 9 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Coke.</hi> After hearing what was urged on both ſides, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29442:19"/> Juſtices ſay, <hi>They had conferred with the Judges of the Common-Pleas upon all the Points objected, And they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, That none of the Objections had any thing in them to arreſt the Judgment,</hi> and therefore <hi>Baggot</hi> recovered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The only Reflections I will at preſent make upon this Caſe is, That altho, what is referred unto by my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> might be, Originally, the Argument of <hi>Baggot</hi>'s Counſel only, yet ſurely in a Point of ſuch Conſequence as this, the Judges would not have let theſe matters paſs without ſome Check or Cenſure, if they had not approved them: They would not have given Judgment on the ſide of thoſe who argued in that manner, without diſtinguiſhing what they did agree unto, and what was not to be allowed of, if any part of what they had laid down, had not been agreeable to the Law and their Opinions. As Affairs then ſtood, there was much greater danger, that the Judges, who owed their Offices to the Power in poſſeſſion, would leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and vilifie the Acts of the caſt-off, diſpoſſeſſed Prince; and that the Counſel would be afraid of ſpeaking up to the full, what their Cauſe would bear; Then that extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant things ſhould be aſſerted at the Bar, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſs unreproved from the Bench, but have the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of a Reſolution of the Court on their ſide; and that a very ſolemn one, upon Advice with the other Judges; which muſt be ſingly upon that point, and not any of the others, they not being worth the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate or haeſitation.</p>
            <p>I think this were ſufficient, but I will add this further Obſervation; That there never has been in any Times ſince, (the Times of moſt undoubtedly rightful Kings) any contradiction to this Opinion, or ſo much as a Quaere put upon it. <hi>Brook</hi> in the Abridging of it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends it with a <hi>Nota,</hi> as a thing worth obſerving. <hi>Coke, Hales,</hi> and <hi>Bridgman</hi> in Print declare this to be Law: Our Author is the firſt <hi>hardy</hi> Man that has un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29442:19"/> to ſet himſelf againſt ſo generally a received Opinion: He has taken pains in it I confeſs; but that he has not ſo throughly weighed it, as he ought, appears by the Anſwer he gives to that part, quoted to prove, That a Pardon granted by a King out of Poſſeſſion is <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f</hi> 24.</note> void: If he had read the words over carefully, he would have found they amount to thus much in <hi>Engliſh: If</hi> 
               <note place="margin">9 <hi>E</hi> 4. 2.</note> 
               <hi>he that is now King, in the time of</hi> Henry VI. <hi>had made a Charter of Pardon, it would be void even</hi> Now; <hi>for every one who grants a Pardon muſt be King in Fact.</hi> Theſe words won't admit of the Evaſion of its being void <hi>in Effect only, and in its Operation,</hi> not from a want of Authority to grant it, but of Strength to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force and ſupport it. The only Judge that ſpeaks pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly (for they were tickliſh Times, and they thought fit to act very cautiouſly for fear of giving Offence) was <hi>Billing.</hi> What he ſays, plainly proves, what our Author elſewhere will not admit, That the Office of King and the Royalty it ſelf is in the King <hi>de facto,</hi> while he is in Poſſeſſion. This <hi>Billing</hi>'s words, as quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Author, prove: There he gives a Reaſon <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 16.</note> why the Legitimation by <hi>H.</hi> 6. ſhould be good, <hi>viz. That 'tis an Act of Grace, and it belongs to every King by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Office</hi> (of which Office he took <hi>H.</hi> 6. to be poſſeſſed) <hi>to do Acts of Juſtice and Grace:</hi> His other caſe of Exemptions, put in the ſame place, proves as <note place="margin">9 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Br. Exemp.</hi> 4.</note> much: For if he were not poſſeſſed of the Royalty it ſelf, he could not make any Grant to the Subject, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Intereſt to bind his Succeſſor, or of Eaſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Subject in the time of a ſucceeding Prince, from what the Law ſubjects or obliges him unto.</p>
            <p>But our Author has found an Inſtance, wherein it was <note place="margin">Def. <hi>f.</hi> 41.</note> held, that Grants of a King <hi>de facto</hi> to the Prejudice of a King <hi>de jure,</hi> are not valid: If I ſhould tell him, that after the rightful Heir (at leaſt he that pretended to be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29442:20"/> ſo, and to avoid his Grant upon that ground) had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to ſubmit to him as his King for his Life, he was not an Uſurper upon him; then his Caſe will prove too much. But the thing it ſelf is not to be wondred at, that a ſucceeding King ſhould <hi>find</hi> or <hi>make</hi> a Reaſon for the reſumption of Crown Lands. There are People abroad in the World that would have helpt <hi>Henry</hi> II. to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Revenues of the Crown are ſo far a Truſt in themſelves, being given for the Support of the Government and Defence of the Kingdom, that they are not of Right alienable.</p>
            <p>But, to return to <hi>Baggot</hi>'s Caſe, I agree, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil do not argue, or the Judges determine (as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 17.</note> obſerves) from any Statute of this Realm: There was not any ſuch, nor any need of one. Common Law and common Reaſon juſtified their Reſolution. And if the Reaſon of the Thing, and Neceſſity of Government determined that caſe to them, where there was not any thing elſe to Govern it: Had not that Man need have a great deal of Wit and Subtilty who undertakes to prove, That as plain words in an Act of Parliament as can be deviſed, having the ſame Reaſon and Neceſſity to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force their being taken in their common and ordinary ſenſe, ought to be expounded away by the Judges into quite another thing, only to avoid their falling in with that reaſonable and convenient ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But this is not the only Book-caſe before the Statute of <hi>H.</hi> 7. which Rules our Point in effect. When <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. had obtained an entire Victory, killed King <hi>Richard</hi> in the Field, and was Proclaimed King, he reſolved ſoon to call a Parliament: One of the ends of his doing it ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> ſays, was, <hi>To have the Attainders of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bac.</hi> Hiſt. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>f.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>all his Party (which were in no ſmall number) reverſed, and all Acts of Hoſtility, by them done in his Quarrel, remitted and diſcharged:</hi> And accordingly Acts were
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29442:20"/> paſſed to that purpoſe. But before it was done, a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in Law was moved. Divers of the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable favourers of the King's Party, during the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, were attainted by Outlawries and otherwiſe for that cauſe: Or, as my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it, <hi>His Partakers were attainted for Offences incident to his Service and Succour.</hi> Many of theſe were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned Knights and Burgeſſes for the Parliament; the Judges are adviſed with upon it, who forthwith aſſemble in the Exchequer-Chamber, and all agree, <hi>That the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con ubi ſup.</hi> 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 4. <hi>Br.</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 37.</note> 
               <hi>Knights and Burgeſſes who were attainted, ought not to come to the Houſe till a Law were paſſed for the Reverſal of their Attainders; nor ought to be in the Houſe at the time of the Reverſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they went further, and unanimouſly Reſolved, That there was no manner of Neceſſity to do any thing for the Reverſal of the King's Attainder (who was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted too;) For that <hi>Eo facto, that he took upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Royal Dignity to be King, he was diſcharged of all Incapacities, and needed not any Act for the Reverſal of his Attainder.</hi> My Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>'s Remark upon this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution is, That it was <hi>A grave and ſafe Opinion and Advice, mixed with Law and Convenience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, in this Reſolution, the Judges muſt either take <hi>H.</hi> 7. to have a Right to the Crown, or that he had not, but was an Uſurper. That they took the former for granted, is, I think, very plain: Or at leaſt they muſt know, that the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (whoſe Cauſe he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took, and with whom, <hi>by Pact precedent with the party who brought him in, he was to Marry)</hi> had ſo. If they did ſo, then they plainly determined that a Conviction of a Man under an Uſurper, for High Treaſon, where the very Act of the Treaſon was, Adherence unto, and Attempts to recover the Rights of the diſpoſſeſſed injured Prince, ſtill remains, even after the Rightful Prince has
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29442:21"/> regained poſſeſſion of the Throne; ſince all Incapacities continued upon thoſe <hi>Loyal</hi> Men, till their Convictions were Reverſed by Parliament; That is, till a <hi>new</hi> Law was made to help them: Till that was done, thoſe who had the Execution of the preſent Laws only, could not ſay other than that the Offence whereof they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed (which was an Attempt againſt the Prince then in poſſeſſion) was High Treaſon; and they were ſtill obnoxious to the Puniſhments the Laws inflict on Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; although what they attempted was done to ſerve and ſupport the Intereſts of the Rightful Princes.</p>
            <p>If the Judges took <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. to be an Uſurper, yet we gain this point by their ſecond Reſolution: They agree him to be inveſted with the Royal Authority by his <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Crown,</hi> and the Submiſſion of the People: By that, his Natural Perſon is changed, and ſo <hi>conſolidated with the Politick Capacity,</hi> Plow. Com. 238. <hi>b.</hi> that every Imperfection was purged, and all the Objections that lay either againſt his Perſon by <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. Attainder, or againſt his Title, which was for ever condemned by Act <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Temp. H.</hi> 6.</note> of Parliament, removed.</p>
            <p>And this Opinion of the Judges in <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's caſe was not the firſt Inſtance of this kind, as appears by the Caſe of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. mentioned by <hi>Townſend,</hi> who after his Reſumption of the Crown held a Parliament, though <note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 5. <hi>b. Br.</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 105.</note> he were before attainted and diſabled; <hi>For,</hi> ſays the Book, <hi>all that was void when he took the Crown upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither was the Notion of the Perſon being changed by the Aſſuming the Crown, new, or framed for that particular Caſe: For we find that when <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Royal Eſtate upon himſelf (and he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly an Uſurper) it was found neceſſary to make a Statute in the firſt Year of his Reign, That <hi>where he was enfeoffed joyntly with others to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, the other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feoffees</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:29442:21"/> 
               <hi>ſhould ſtand ſeized to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe; where he was ſole ſeized, the whole Eſtate ſhould be veſted in the Ceſtuique uſe;</hi> and this, becauſe by the taking the Politick Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city on himſelf, his Natural Perſon was gone, and <hi>Seignior le Roy</hi> can't ſtand ſeized to an Uſe.</p>
            <p>If the Treaſon of Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> in the time of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bac. H.</hi> 7. <hi>f</hi> 134 Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. were what my Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> and our Author re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it to be, <hi>viz.</hi> his ſaying, <hi>That if he were ſure that</hi> Perkin <hi>were King</hi> Edward<hi>'s Son, he would never bear Arms againſt him:</hi> It goes a very great way in the ſhewing what the Opinion of that time was; and that the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers don't agree, that the Statute of 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged the ſenſe of <hi>Seignior le Roy,</hi> but that they thought 'twas always the Duty of the private Subject to pay his Obedience to the poſſeſſion. This Caſe, I ſay, proves not only that <hi>it is Treaſon for a private perſon to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule the Title of the King that is in poſſeſſion,</hi> which my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> deduces from the words, but it makes it Treaſon to refuſe his Active Obedience for the Support of that King in poſſeſſion, even againſt him, who, he is ſatisfied, has a better Right. This I am ſure muſt be the Opinion of thoſe who condemned him; and the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian in that place takes Notice that <hi>the Judges of that time were great and learned Men, and the three Chief of them of the Privy Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſhew how far the Law-givers of that time lookt upon private Subjects to be bound up by ſuch Acts of Government made in the time of an Uſurper, as our Author would have called <hi>Inauthoritative, null, and void,</hi> until an equal Power have adnulled, or decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to be ſo, I will refer my Author to the Year-Book, 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>f.</hi> 5. <hi>b.</hi> There he will find a ſpecial <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morandum</hi> of the Reverſal of an Act of Parliament, which Act was ſo falſe and ſcandalous, that, upon Advice of the Juſtices it was not thought fit to recite the Matter or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29442:22"/> Effect of it in the Act of Reverſal, leſt it ſhould remain in remembrance: And this Act was made directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Right of the Children of <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. to Baſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize them; yet a ſpecial Note is made of it, That ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been done by a Parliament, there was a neceſſity for another Act of Parliament to take this Scandalous Bill off from the Roll. They it ſeems did not look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the private Judgment of the Clerk of the Parliament to be ſufficient to adjudge of our Author's <hi>Nullities in themſelves;</hi> though that private Judgment determined in favour of what they lookt upon to be the Right, joyned with the Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider the Statute 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 1. the Preamble of which declares, <hi>That the Subjects, by reaſon of their Duty of Allegiance, are bound to ſerve their Prince and Soveraign Lord for the time being, in his Wars, for the Defence of him and the Land, against every Rebellion, Power, and Might reared againſt him, and with him to enter into Service, if the Caſe ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that whatever the Succeſs fall out to be, 'tis not reaſonable, but againſt all Laws, Reaſon, and good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that they, ſo going with him in his Wars, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his Perſon, or being elſewhere by his Command, ſhould loſe or forfeit any thing, for doing their true Duty and Service of Allegiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thereupon 'tis Enacted and Eſtabliſhed by that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>That no perſon from thenceforth, that attend upon the King and Soveraign Lord of this Land for the time being, in his perſon, or do him true and faithful Service of Allegiance, ſhall for that be vexed or troubled, either by Act of Parliament or otherwiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:29442:22"/>
            <p> Our Author by what has been already ſaid, will find the miſtake that he is under, when he ſays the Lawyers agree, <hi>That it is this Statute only, which has extended</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Def. <hi>f.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>the words</hi> Seignior le Roy <hi>in</hi> 25 Edw. 3. <hi>to comprehend an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper in poſſeſſion, as King for the time being, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before,</hi> 25 Edw. 3. <hi>meant Lawful and Rightful Kings only.</hi> What is already ſaid to that purpoſe, will, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, ſatisfie every one, that the Judges, who are Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors of Statutes, and were to put that Act in Execution, did never look upon themſelves as competent for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining the Title of the Crown, but lookt upon him to be <hi>Seignior le Roy</hi> within that Act, who executed the Office of King, in adminiſtring Juſtice, and protecting and defending the People. The end of that Statute 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. as I have ſaid before, was not ſo much to make a ſolemn Declaration of the Law (which all through it is taken for granted, as an indiſputable Opinion of that time at leaſt) as it was to condemn the way that had too often been lately taken, to deſtroy the good Effects of the Law in that particular; by making ſo many revengeful Acts of Attainder upon every change. They endeavoured, as far as the Nature of the thing would admit of it, to tie up, even the Hands of future Parliaments, from acting contrary to that eaſie and reaſonable Rule: And having done that, little thought they had left a Liberty to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Men to vent their Opinions and Fancies, raiſe Scruples in the minds of People, and write Books to prove that a King is no King, nor to be obeyed: And that a bare Right to be a King, (which ſuppoſes and imports in the very terms themſelves his being diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Throne and Office) makes him, the Only Perſon meant by the words <hi>Seignior le Roy;</hi> whereas he that is in full poſſeſſion of the Office and Government, is quite out of them.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29442:23"/>
            <p> But to ſhew our Author that the Notion was not quite new, and firſt introduced by this Statute to ſerve a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular turn, nor the Opinion of Lawyers only, I would refer him to a Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>An Hiſtorical Account of ſome things relating to the Nature of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> there, <hi>f.</hi> 40. He will find the words of a great many Hiſtorians quoted, which I will not Tranſcribe, all cenſuring the Act of thoſe Nobles, who, upon diſlike to <hi>William Rufus</hi> that was poſſeſſed of the Government, did endeavour to dethrone him, and advance his Elder Brother <hi>Robert</hi> to the Throne, as an <hi>Execrable Fact,</hi> calling them <hi>Traiterous, Perfidious,</hi> and <hi>Perjured</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: And declaring, that they who ſided with <hi>William,</hi> were Faithful to <hi>their Earthly Lord:</hi> Though as appears in the ſame page, thoſe very Hiſtorians agreed, that <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> had manifeſt Right to the Kingdom by courſe of Hereditary Succeſſion.</p>
            <p>Nay, for want of other Authorities, I would venture to make Uſe once more of our Author's Act 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. which not only very fully aſſerts, <hi>That the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers were by their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation poſſeſſed of the Regal Power, Eſtate, Dignity, Preheminence, Poſſeſſion, and Lordſhip of</hi> England, to which purpoſe it was quoted before, but goes on; <hi>By</hi> Edward <hi>the Fourth's removing</hi> Henry <hi>the Sixth from the Occupation, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, Intruſion, Reign, and Governance of the ſame Realm of</hi> England <hi>and Lordſhip, to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Comfort and Conſolation of all his Subjects and Liege Men, plenteouſly joyed to be amoved and departed from the</hi> Obeyſance <hi>and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> &amp;c. Our Author may with little pains learn what the import of the Term <hi>Obeyſance</hi> was at that time lookt upon to be.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:29442:23"/>
            <p> I confeſs, the Act of 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. to me ſeems to make the moſt Solemn Declaration of this, as a Rule not to be varied from, That Allegiance is due to the King for the time being; And 'tis the Subjects Duty to pay it to him: And I would deſire no more from any Man, but that he would read it over attentively, to make him a Judge between my Author and me, whether fuller words could reaſonably be thought of to ſilence all Opinions to the contrary: Let us ſee how our Author quits him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from them.</p>
            <p>I believe he will not rely much upon the firſt Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he ſeems to make, <hi>That only the enacting part of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>a Statute is Law:</hi> He brings it in with an <hi>If,</hi> and never takes it up again: ſo that at preſent, without detaining my Reader in the Proof, that it is day when the Sun ſhines, I will take it for granted, That what an Act of Parliament recites or declares to be Law, is ſo. And then inſtead of what our Author has ſet down as <hi>all that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>this Statute proves;</hi> It proves thus much at leaſt, <hi>That it is the Duty of every private Subject, to attend and pay his Allegiance to the King in Poſſeſſion; And contrary to the Laws as they ſtand at preſent, and to all Reaſon and good Conſcience, even for a Parliament, whoſe Power can't be withſtood, to make his ſo doing Penal to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will agree to him, that <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. himſelf had not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed <note place="margin">Def. <hi>f.</hi> 42.</note> according to this Rule, but made uſe of the ſame Liberty former Kings and Parliaments had taken, of reak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Vengeance on thoſe that oppoſed him: He was too fond of the Crown; He would not elſe have ſet up for it, without any Right at firſt: And it is not to be imagined that he, who made no ſcruple of obtaining it againſt Right, and put off ſo long the making his Poſſeſſion juſt, when he had ſuch an Opportunity of doing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29442:24"/> it, by marrying her who had the undoubted Right, would make any difficulty of ſecuring himſelf in that poſſeſſion by any means whatſoever: This criminates him in his Morals, proves him to be a Man whom Intereſt did Rule, to the doing things which he was convinced were againſt Reaſon and Conſcience; and proves no more. Nay, I muſt offer in his Excuſe, that he afterwards made what amends he could, by condemning his own former ill, and uſing his utmoſt endeavours, that the poor Subject ſhould never be harraſſed and puniſhed at that barbarous rate more.</p>
            <p>Can a Man be real in Objecting to a Law, agreed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Caſe <hi>f.</hi> 29.</note> and paſſed by thoſe Perſons, whom the whole Body of the Kingdom thought fitteſt to repreſent them, and to whoſe Integrity and Underſtanding they entruſted their deareſt Concerns: That it was made by an Uſurper in Title, and 'tis not <hi>(he determines it)</hi> for the good <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f.</hi> 18.</note> of the Community: Yet ſuch Laws as are for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, he agrees, are valid, though paſſed by an Uſurper. Nay, our Author goes further, and enquires, by helps <hi>dehors</hi> as the Lawyers call it, Foreign to the words of the Act it ſelf, what the End and Deſign of the King <hi>under-hand</hi> was, in procuring the Statute; and that, he diſcovers to be nothing leſs, than to ſecure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Unjuſt Uſurpation; becauſe <hi>Perkin Warbeck</hi> happened to be up in Arms about that time; ſo that he propoſed to himſelf to ſecure his Title by that Act againſt the Houſe of <hi>York:</hi> And that <hi>Deſign</hi> ſhall make this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <hi>void,</hi> though <hi>Perkin</hi> prove the Son of a Beggerly <hi>Jew,</hi> and the Queen, who had long before been Crowned, and Reigned with him, had undoubtedly the true Right to the Crown.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:29442:24"/>
            <p> Neither can I yet work my ſelf up to think, That the Enacting a new Law, in a particular Caſe, contrary to the purview of a precedent general one, is a total Repeal of that Law. As for inſtance: Suppoſe in the Caſe of my Lord <hi>Strafford;</hi> Becauſe he was attainted by Act of Parliament, without Proof by two Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and for Facts, none of which, conſidered ſingly and by themſelves, amounted to High Treaſon, but made a great accumulative Crime, therefore, if it had not been for the Caution uſed, That the like ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be drawn into Precedent or Example, from that time forward, a load of leſſer Crimes muſt have grown up into one High Treaſon, and the Statutes of 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had ſtood entirely Repealed in thoſe points: <hi>They,</hi> for ſo much, <hi>having in effect been declared to be null and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>invalid by a Lawful King and Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſides this, as to his Inſtance of the Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland</hi>'s Attainder (not to mention a great many other things which hinder its amounting to any manner of Proof of what he brings it for) I muſt tell him, that the Act confirming that Attainder did not in the leaſt contradict the Statute 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. for that he was attainted upon the Statute 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. without being within any help from this Statute; And therefore his Attainder was Legal, though it had never been declared ſo by Act of Parliament; though the Queen thought fit to make matters ſure, and put that in for Company, with the Attainders of ſeveral others, who were attainted upon other accounts. The Lady <hi>Jane</hi> was never ſuch a <hi>Queen in poſſeſſion</hi> as is within this Law, or to be accounted ſo: She was, 'tis true, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by ſome few of her Friends, and ſo was the late
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29442:25"/> Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> in the Weſt? But did ever any one ſay or imagine, that ſuch a Poſſeſſion entituled one to the Allegiance of the whole Kingdom? That is as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant on the one ſide, as our Author's Opinion on the other: Temper them, and make it neceſſary to the obtaining ſuch a Poſſeſſion without a Juſt Title, as ſhall claim the Duty of Subjection, That there be a quiet and peaceable Submiſſion to the Perſon who fills the Throne by the Body of the Nation, a Recognition of him by the States, the Treaſure, Power, and Strength of the Kingdom in his hands, Publick Juſtice admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred only by thoſe that are commiſſionated by him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and you'll find the <hi>Golden Mean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Obſervation made by the Author, That Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was no more than Proclaimed, when the Duke was Tried and Executed by her Authority, makes nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this: She had <hi>de jure</hi> a Title, and a notorious one too, for that the Succeſſion was limited unto her by Name in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Acts for the Succeſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her being his Eldeſt Daughter: And I will grant to him, that he is much in the right, when he affirms, <hi>That</hi> (at this day) <hi>the next Heir of the Blood is actually</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caſe. <hi>f</hi> 48. Def. <hi>f.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>King, and in poſſeſſion, from the very moment of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor's Death, and has a Right to the Allegiance of his Subjects from that time.</hi> I have told him all along, though leſs may amount to a diſturbing or diſquieting him, that there muſt be more than a bare Proclaiming of another to diſpoſſeſs him: The affirming of which, is not in any ſort inconſiſtent with their Principles, who maintain, that Submiſſion is due to a King, who has obtained a <hi>full</hi> poſſeſſion of the Throne. So that the Author might have ſpared the <hi>mannerly</hi> Queſtion he puts to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> upon this Occaſion. <hi>Defence, f.</hi> 55.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:29442:25"/>
            <p> His Argument is the ſame, <hi>Caſe. f.</hi> 34. King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight having indulged himſelf very greatly in the taking and diſmiſſing of Wives, did from time to time, according to the run of his Affections, make ſeveral Laws for the Settlement of the Succeſſion; and laid great Penalties on the Infringers of thoſe Laws, and particularly on ſuch Perſons as ſhould Uſurp upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to whom, by the plain and expreſs words of the reſpective Acts, the Crown was limited and entailed: Theſe Laws were very neceſſary at that time, becauſe from the unuſual Liberty he had taken in that particular, of neceſſity <hi>great ambiguities and doubts muſt ariſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſeveral Titles, which might be pretended to the Crown, and thence would probably enſue great effuſion of Blood,</hi> &amp;c. as the Statutes 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 22. &amp;c. ſpeak.</p>
            <p>To prevent this, he very prudently takes care to tell his Subjects, by Act of Parliament, where their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſhall be paid, names the Perſons in courſe as they ſhould ſucceed; And forbids, under the greateſt Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, any <hi>One</hi> to Uſurp upon or Claim a Title otherwiſe than according to thoſe Limitations. Theſe Acts (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that Acts of Parliament can alter the Hereditary Courſe of Deſcent, which <hi>perhaps</hi> my Author and ſome few others will not agree, but I can't bring my ſelf to make any doubt of) amount to no more than this: That any who ſhould offer to break through that Limitation, ſhould be Uſurpers, and thoſe that ſhould aid and aſſiſt them therein, be Traytors. I have not yet pretended that thoſe who aid and abett one that has no Title, and put him into the poſſeſſion of the Throne, are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; or that the Act of Exalting an Uſurper to the Throne, is juſtifiable: All that I contend for, is, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29442:26"/> to them after they are in quiet poſſeſſion: So that theſe Acts make nothing for what my Author in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to prove, or againſt what I propoſe to my ſelf to defend: They laid not any Obligation on Conſcience contrary to the Statute 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. But provided only to ſecure the Poſſeſſion to thoſe mentioned in that Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, by making it Death for any to attempt, or aſſiſt in the breaking of it. But I will for once ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, thoſe Acts had in expreſs words Enacted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That, if Perſons contrary to thoſe Limitations, did get into the Throne, and obtain a full Poſſeſſion of it, all thoſe who had been Aſſiſtant unto them in their ſo doing; Or who ſhould afterwards ſubmit to them, ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as Traytors: Yet this would amount to no more, than that the general precedent Law, and the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, was Suſpended and Repealed as to this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſtance; As if it had in expreſs terms ſaid, In theſe particulars, when the Right of Succeſſion is ſo plainly determined to the Subject by a competent Power, that there is no poſſibility of his being miſtaken in it, unleſs he be ſo, <hi>wilfully:</hi> Whoever attempts any thing contrary to them, ſhall not have benefit of Indemnity from any former Laws, but the Perſon ſet up, and all his Adherents, and thoſe that ſupport him in his Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, ſhall be puniſhed as Traytors. This would have been ſo far from a total Repeal, that it would rather have been a Confirmation of the precedent Laws in all other caſes but thoſe particular Inſtances.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:29442:26"/>
            <p> The ſame is to be ſaid to the Oaths enjoyned by thoſe Laws of <hi>H.</hi> 8. for the eſtabliſhing the Succeſſion: Suppoſing them to have laid an Obligation upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, contrary to the general Purvieu of the 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. for the time to which they extended, yet the matter of them is long ſince ceas'd: And I can't find any Reaſon or Authority to prove, that a contrary proviſion, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a fixed and determinate time, does, <hi>for ever,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal a general poſitive Law.</p>
            <p>The late Oaths of Obedience in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> and King <hi>James</hi>'s times, have left the Title to the Crown, as general and unſettled as it was in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 7. So that the Subjects are now obliged by Vertue of thoſe Oaths to the true Succeſſors in the Kingly Power; and I think what is already ſaid, makes it plain, that a private Subject muſt look upon thoſe who are in full and quiet poſſeſſion of the Throne, to be truly and lawfully ſo, till they are either deveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Power, or their Right condemned by thoſe that have Authority to do it. The word <hi>Heirs,</hi> I own is joyned to <hi>Succeſſors</hi> in theſe Oaths; but if either, as the Lawyers ſay, <hi>Haeres dicitur ab Haereditate,</hi> or the words of themſelves, being joynt, extend only to ſuch an Heir as is a Succeſſor, (as I muſt think, till I hear better Arguments to the contrary, then I ever yet have met with,) theſe Oaths will make for, not againſt me.</p>
            <p>However I can't find any contradiction between theſe Oaths and the Statute 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. They do not ſpeak <hi>Ad idem.</hi> 'Tis too groſs to be put upon any Man at this time of day, to ſay, Theſe Oaths oblige us to any certain Perſon under the name <hi>Heirs and Succeſſors</hi> during the life of the Poſſeſſor; ſo that the end of theſe Oaths was to put an Obligation on Conſcience to prevent the Act of Uſurpation, and preſerve the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29442:27"/> Government Hereditary: The Act of <hi>H.</hi> 7. ſuppoſes that ſettled, and declares what a Subject is to do when it is ſo.</p>
            <p>Beſides I think the Lawyers generally agree it for a Rule, <hi>That it muſt be a very plain Contrariety, and abſolute Inconſiſtency, that ſhall effect a Repeal of a former by a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Statute, without expreſs words of Repeal: And that a Law being once eſtabliſhed, with the univerſal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the whole Kingdom, it muſt not be look'd upon to be abrogated by any ſtrained Conſtruction of general and ambiguous Words.</hi> And if this be true, I am ſure the Stat. 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. ſtands yet unrepealed by any of the Laws our Author has produc'd againſt it.</p>
            <p>I can't but wonder to hear a private perſon deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining, That a <hi>Statute,</hi> That is, a Law of the Land, <note place="margin">Caſe <hi>f.</hi> 36. Defence <hi>f.</hi> 47.</note> muſt be lookt upon as <hi>null and invalid, in reſpect of the matter of it,</hi> becauſe in his Opinion, <hi>It eſtabliſhes Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> and is made, as he ſays, <hi>Caſe</hi> f. 32. <hi>To the diſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of a lawful King,</hi> That is, a King of the Laws making. In plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> this amounts to thus much; The Title which the King has to the Crown, tho it belongs not to him, either by the Law of God or Nature, but by a poſitive Law of the Land, can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be wholly defeated, or abridged in part, nor the Power or Rights of it moderated for a certain time, by as poſitive a Law: This is a very Paradox, and needs a man of our Author's Learning and induſtry to make it look colourable.</p>
            <p>This and a great deal more of our Author's argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Caſe</hi> f. 37, 38, 39, 40, 41. will fall to the ground, if he will, till he proves the contrary, admit, 1. That the word <hi>King</hi> does not neceſſarily import in it ſelf, in all places, any certain and determinate Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges; but that the poſitive Laws of the Land are Bounds unto, and may preſcribe the Order and Form of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29442:27"/> legal Ligeance, and may enlarge or abridge thoſe Rights which the name <hi>King,</hi> according to the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral extent and ſenſe of the Word would have enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled the Perſon unto. And <hi>2dly,</hi> if I could prevail upon him not to lay ſo much ſtreſs upon that Word, when 'tis joyned to <hi>de jure;</hi> not ſuppoſe him ſtill in poſſeſſion of the Office, but fairly Engliſh it, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who has Right to the Office and Government, but is wrongfully put out of it.</p>
            <p>The fallacy grounded upon the latter of theſe, runs through ſo many parts of the Book, that more than half his arguing part might have been ſaved, if he he would have ſtated it truly: If he would but agree to me, that the word <hi>King,</hi> is rather a name of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Office than perſonal Right, there would be an end of a great part of the Diſpute. Let us turn it into <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> and ſee how the Queſtion will then ſtand. <hi>VVhether in this Government, the Subjects are to pay their Service and Duty to him that is in Fact their Governour, tho he obtained the Government by unjuſt means, or to him who ought to be their Governour, but plainly is not, nor has a Power to exerciſe any Acts of Government, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther over, or in defence of them.</hi> I am apt to think it would be an hard thing for a man of very great parts, ſo much as to amuſe any man, if he would ſtate the caſe ſo; or to perſwade him, that the Duty of the perſon governed, has any relation to the Right of the perſon, diſtinct from the Office. In ſhort, That private man goes beyond his Line who looks upon him that is out of Poſſeſſion to be his King, or acts accordingly, when the Throne is filled with a Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor qualified as I have before ſet down: And if ſo, the Statute 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. implies nothing of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction which the <hi>Caſe f.</hi> 53. fixes upon it.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:29442:28"/>
            <p> I would not be miſtaken in this, ſo as to have it objected to me, That I am coming within the reach of that <hi>miſchievous Poſition</hi> of ſeparating the Perſon and Office: It was always my Opinion that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it (as it has been formerly made uſe of) would be in conſequence very pernicious and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Rules of Law. The miſchief of that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is, the diſtinguiſhing between the Kings Acts and Capacities, while he is a King and in Poſſeſſion: to ſay ſome of his Acts are thoſe of his natural perſon, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from his politick Capacity, and upon that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to take a liberty of acting againſt his natural Perſon, as ſuppoſing that diſtinct from his politick Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity. This appears to be the Miſchief, by what is quoted out of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe; where 'tis ſaid, <hi>That Lige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Defence <hi>f.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>is due to the natural Perſon of the King, which is ever accompanied by the politick Capacity, and the politick Capacity as it were appropriated to the natural Capacity; and 'tis not due to the politick Capacity only, that is, to the Crown and Kingdom diſtinct from his natural Capacity.</hi> And by the Act of Uniformity, which declares it a Trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Poſition, <hi>to take Arms by the King's Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Perſon:</hi> This ſhews, that the ill of the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction condemned there, lies in the ſeparating the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities when they are really joyned; that is, when the natural Perſon is in poſſeſſion of the Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: to ſet him up to fight againſt himſelf, his own Authority againſt his Perſon; this is contrary to Law, which, as it appears before, <hi>conſolidates</hi> the natural Perſon with the politick Capacity. I am ſo far from denying this, that it is the ground whereupon I take Obedience to be due to a King <hi>de facto:</hi> But the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous part does not at all reach our Caſe, where we ſuppoſe him, who has a Right to be King, to be utterly diſpoſſeſſed and deveſted of the Office, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29442:28"/> the Right of the Poſſeſſor ſolemnly recognized by the Body of the People: There, 'tis not a nice diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that ſeparates between the Capacities, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident Fact and Truth, common Senſe, and the Laws of the Land; and to the Perſon, as a Perſon deveſted of the Office, Allegiance is not due. That it was a very great wrong unjuſtly to deveſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Office, and put another into it, can't be doubted; and 'tis a part of that wrong, that he is thereby deveſted of that which makes the Relation between him and the People, that of right ought to be his Subjects, and pay him Allegiance; but till he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite the Office to his Perſon, the wrong remains, and the Relation during that time fails.</p>
            <p>It may be very well maintained, that the Statute 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. ſhall have all the Effect and Operation the plain Words of it will reaſonably bear; and yet none of thoſe diſmal Breaches upon the Conſtitution, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitous Conſequences ſet forth, <hi>Caſe</hi> f. 38. at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it.</p>
            <p>That the Fundamental Conſtitution of <hi>England</hi> is a Monarchy, and that ſettled antecedently to any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Law, will be very readily agreed to him by me: But he goes a little too faſt when he infers thence, <hi>That therefore there muſt of neceſſity be ſome certain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in every Age, in whom the Conſtitution veſts a Right; by vertue of which, he is lawful and rightful King of this Realm:</hi> For 'tis not of abſolute neceſſity that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Race and Family ſhould be part of that Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>May it not be rationally ſuppoſed that the Framers of our Government proceeded by degrees; firſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated what the form of the Government in general ſhould be; and fixt upon a Monarchy: What kind of Monarchy would make another ſtep, and I will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29442:29"/> that, to prevent the ill effects of Ambition and canvaſing for it, they agreed, it ſhould be an Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary one, ſuch as ſhould be governed by the courſe of deſcent, not elective: This in common ſence it muſt be preſumed they did, before they came to fix upon certain Perſons or Families, into whoſe hands they ſhould put the Government: Nay 'tis impoſſible to maintain our Government to be a limited or mixt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy in its nature, without ſuch a ſuppoſition: ſo that I can't by any means look upon the particular Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to be any part of the Original and Fundamental Conſtitution; but at moſt, only a ſecondary one, a putting the Conſtitution that they had agreed upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Act and Execution: And therefore it may very well be, for any thing that I can find in reaſon to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, That the Government may fall into the hands of perſons, that have no relation to the Line of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces firſt ſubmitted unto, who ſhall yet have a Right by vertue of the Fundamental Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>Our Author has almoſt yielded me this in his firſt <note place="margin">Caſe f. 2.</note> Preliminary: But to vary that inſtance a little: Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe during the Life of him that ſhould happen to be the laſt of the Race of our Princes, He and his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhould agree, that after his death another Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and his Race ſhould ſucceed to the Throne accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the directions and Meaſures preſcribed by the preſent Laws, would any body queſtion his right to ſucceed? The Fundamental Government would be ſtill the ſame; A mixt Monarchy according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conſtitution: And I cannot perſwade my ſelf that in the Conſtitution it ſelf, the intereſt of the particular Family was ſo highly regarded, as that the one muſt neceſſarily fall with the other. Our Author indeed I find thinks, that becauſe <hi>Hereditary</hi> is joyned to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, <note place="margin">Defence f. 12.</note> when once it falls to another Family, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29442:29"/> is gone. An Eſtate in Fee-ſimple has this Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that it is an Eſtate of Inheritance: That is, an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary</hi> Eſtate: If therefore the poſſeſſor transfer it to a Stranger, muſt the Eſtate be gone? ſuppoſe <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary</hi> ſhould be expounded in the one caſe as well as the other, to ſignifie ſuch an Eſtate as will of its own nature deſcend to Heirs, and veſt in them a Title if the Diſcent, be not interrupted, by ſuch methods as the Law allows of: And be lookt upon, to be ſet in oppoſition to <hi>Elective</hi> in the one caſe, and an Eſtate <hi>determinable upon the death of the Party</hi> in the other.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I ſhould think it an exceeding of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, for a King and Parliament to turn this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into a Common-wealth; for they act under the preſent Frame and Conſtitution: Whenever that is diſſolved, they have no longer a right to act as Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives of the People; ſo that they cannot, <hi>for them</hi> ſubmit to a new form of Government. To the doing any thing of that kind, there muſt be firſt a diſſolution of the preſent Frame, and then, either all muſt joyn in the erecting a new one, or they muſt, after they are reinſtated in the Liberty which they had by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, agree upon ſome method of being repreſented, and delegate their Right and Power to ſuch Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives. This ſhews that this opinion does not offer at the warranting a ſubjection to any Uſurper, but ſuch an one as is in poſſeſſion, under the form the preſent Conſtitution allows. All others, not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this Frame of Government, are in, <hi>above</hi> or <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> the Law, and conſequently have not Right to <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> Allegiance, which is the reſult of the preſent Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of Laws made for the preſervation of that. Such a Power may hold me in ſubjection as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Man or a Slave, and for the obtaining my Life or Freedom, I may anew ſtipulate with them;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29442:30"/> and from that time they may juſtly claim my Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance by vertue of that ſtipulation: I may ſtipulate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, I ſay, if my former allegiance obſtruct it not: But that may very well fall out to be the caſe, for till there is an entire diſſolution of the Government (whether that muſt be done by the agreement of all who have an intereſt in it, or that a majority will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the reſt) I own that Allegiance is due from every private Man ſome where; And I am ſure I may, without contradicting any thing I have hitherto ſaid, fix the right to it in the Perſon of the King <hi>de jure,</hi> where the Kingly Office is not exerciſed by any other: But where another is poſſeſſed of the very Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which is wrought into the Conſtitution it ſelf, and he puts in execution all the ſame Laws by which rightful Kings ought to govern; to that Office, and the Perſon poſſeſſed of it, my Allegiance is by thoſe Laws due, and no Law makes me a Judge of the King's Title.</p>
            <p>And it was upon this Ground undoubtedly that my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hales</hi> (who plainly held the Law in the <hi>Caſe</hi> of the Statute 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. to be as I now main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it) would never try any Treaſon or other Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt the State, as our Author ſays, while he was <note place="margin">Caſe, <hi>f.</hi> 4.</note> Judge under <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return: What if I ſhould ſuppoſe, (as ſome <hi>wiſe</hi> Men have affirmed) that when our Anceſtors heretofore ſubmitted to a certain Family, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way occaſion of Factions and making Parties, they confined the Crown to that Family, but did not ſo ſtrictly oblige themſelves to him who ſhould be next in Courſe of deſcent; but that the States of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who repreſent and include the body of the whole People, if they found him abſolutely unquali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and unfit for the Government, might skip over
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29442:30"/> him, ſtill keeping to ſome of that Line. (And ſince what the Original Frame of our Conſtitution was, is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to us with any certainty, by Hiſtory or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Records, that may well be ſuppoſed to be our Conſtitution, if conſtant Practice and Uſage, till very lately, be a probable proof of Right in things where the poſitive Rule is loſt.) If this were the caſe, what would then become of the Suppoſition of <hi>a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Perſon, always lawful and rightful King, by Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caſe <hi>f.</hi> 8. 38.</note> 
               <hi>of the Original Conſtitution,</hi> &amp;c. But not to rely upon this, I muſt take leave to believe what I touch'd upon before, That it was the Form of the Government it ſelf, of which our Anceſtors, who fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, were ſo fond, and not of the particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Family; tho they were by that Form to have the greateſt Truſt and beſt Share (comparing them with particulars, not the whole Body) in it: And therefore I am fully ſatisfied, as I ſaid before, that the very Fundamental Conſtitution may remain, tho the Family ſhould be changed by a Competent Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and that no Injury or Injuſtice is done them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, ſince their Right was given them only by poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Laws, and may therefore be taken away again by the ſame means: And if ſo, after all our Author's ☜ Labour, the Statute 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. does no ways break in upon our Conſtitution. If our Author would but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the words <hi>King de jure,</hi> as I have all through this Paper preſs'd him to do, we ſhould eaſily rid the Stat. 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. of the Contradiction which he ſuppoſes <note place="margin">Caſe, <hi>f.</hi> 39</note> it implies.</p>
            <p>A <hi>King de jure</hi> has a Right to ſomething, as he ſays; that <hi>ſomething</hi> is the poſſeſſion of the Throne, which will conſequently draw the Royalties and Revenues of that, with the Allegiance of the Subject. But till he attains that Poſſeſſion, in vertue of which the Right
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29442:31"/> to thoſe Royalties, Allegiance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> belongs to him, he muſt content himſelf without them.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Anſwer ſerves to his other Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That this Statute is againſt the Law of Nature,</hi> which <note place="margin">Caſe, <hi>f.</hi> 40.</note> our Author from that Huddle of Inconſiſtencies. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe, ſays, <hi>makes Faith, Obedience, and Lige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, due to the lawful King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſome parts of 'em indiſpenſable, and not to be transferred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not worth the while to argue any thing from <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe, the Authority of which can never be of advantage to either ſide, becauſe there is ſcarce any one Propoſition (unleſs it be the very point ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged) advanced through that whole Caſe, as 'tis reported by my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> but what may be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (that is, contradicted) by ſomething elſe of the ſame Author in the ſame Caſe; but to conſider ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reaſon, as much of it as our Author makes uſe of. I will not diſpute at preſent but that Obedience to Governours is due by the Law of Nature; that is, That the Law of Nature does ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it ſelf to Civil Societies when they are fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and in general obliges ſuch as are in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Subjects, to pay their Governours all that Duty, which, according to the Frame of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Laws, is neceſſary to the Maintenance and Welfare of that Society: Other natural Allegiance there is none; nor does the Law of Nature (tho our Author affirm the contrary, without offering any Proof or Reaſon for it) <hi>lay before the Subject any certain Duties which they are to put in practice, whether the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Laws of the Realm enjoyn them or not, and ſuch as no human Authority can diſpence with, as long as they ſtand in the Relation of Prince and Subject.</hi> This is a very wild Notion, and can have no Foundation in Reaſon: Take away the Relative Terms of <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Subject,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:29442:31"/> and ſuppoſe that a Nation ſubmits to a particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon after this manner: He ſhall have Rule over them, and govern according to ſuch particular Rules, as then are, or with their conſent afterwards ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, and none other. Is not all the Freedom which they had by Nature, but their being obliged to ſubmit to the putting thoſe Rules in execution, left with them, and unſubmitted; May not any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Law afterwards alter, enlarge, or abridge thoſe meaſures of Obedience and Submiſſion, which were the Creatures of poſitive Law at firſt? It may be ſaid, it will be inconſiſtent with the name of <hi>King</hi> to have no Allegiance due to him. I would ask the Objector, Which is more reaſonable, that a Notion, the Pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of affirming poſitively what the <hi>natural</hi> Senſe of a Term is, ſhould have Power over, and render inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant, or repeal the plain Words of an expreſs Law; or that the Law ſhould for once frame a new, tho it may be an improper Senſe, for the Terms, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-rule the Grammarian? If the Law ſhould in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words ſay, That he that has a juſt Title to the Crown ſhall be ſtiled <hi>King de jure</hi> while he is out of Poſſeſſion, (tho that is not ſo, nor is that name ever allowed him till he is reſtored:) And he that is in Poſſeſſion <hi>King de facto;</hi> that during the time of his Poſſeſſion a temporary Allegiance ſhall be paid by the People to <hi>him,</hi> and not to the King <hi>de jure:</hi> I think common Senſe will ſay, that there is no inconſiſtency in this, unleſs the words <hi>King de jure</hi> are ſo very Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, that they can't lower their Signification, to a poſitive Law, but muſt eternally carry with them one and the ſame extent of Power and Exerciſe of Authority.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:29442:32"/>
            <p> That the Law of Nature obliges a Man to make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution for Injuries done, I agree, but that muſt be out of what is his own, without Injury to another; elſe, having robbed one, and having nothing of my own wherewith to make him Reparation; I might rob another to do it: So in the preſent Caſe, If I have been acceſſary to the unjuſt diſpoſſeſſing the rightful Prince, nature obliges me to make him what recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence I juſtly may: But if it fall out, that nature does not at all intermeddle with determining what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons have a Right to the Government, <hi>Or make one Man King, the reſt his Subjects,</hi> but that the <note place="margin">Caſe f. 40.</note> Relation between the Perſons governing, and to be governed, and the meaſures of Protection and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thence flowing, are of poſitive Inſtitution, and the Effect of the particular Laws of the Land: And if the Laws of the Land have ſo fixt the Duty of my Allegiance to the King in Poſſeſſion, that, acting in the condition of a private Subject, I can't withdraw it from him, without a breach of thoſe Laws, without taking from him what the Law has given him a Right unto: The Law of Nature can't oblige me to that; nor has the diſpoſſeſſed Prince any Right by the Law of Nature to claim or exact that ſatisfaction from me; ſo that the Statute 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. does not at all thwart or contradict the Law of Nature, or any Duty in diſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly incumbent on the Subject by it.</p>
            <p>This Conſideration will indeed aggravate the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of my contributing towards ſuch an Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and make People that have any ſenſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, very cautious how they venture upon doing a thing of that kind; where the very Act of doing the thing, puts it out of their Power to wipe out any part of their former Sin, by an endeavour to make Reparation, without their contracting a new Guilt.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:29442:32"/>
            <p> Our Author compares the caſe of Obedience due <note place="margin">Caſe <hi>f,</hi> 23.</note> to the King, with the Caſe of the Subject, as to the Protection which the King is obliged to give him: Theſe, I agree, are very fitly conſidered together, as mutually explaining and proving one the other. Let us ſee whether the reaſon of that Caſe will not fully come up to the proof of what I am endeavouring to make out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The King is obliged to maintain his Subjects in their Rights and Properties not only while they are in poſſeſſion, but alſo, when another has diſſeized them by fraud or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence:</hi> True, he is to do the latter (which carries a reſemblance to the caſe in queſtion) as well as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: But it muſt be, according to the meaſures, and purſuing the methods the Law preſcribes. Where a ſubject is diſſeized, Law is to precede force: There muſt be a deciſion by a proper Judge in his favour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there be a reſtoring him to his poſſeſſion: Till that be done, he is to quiet and defend the Poſſeſſour in the Poſſeſſion, tho' gotten by fraud and injuſtice: The King himſelf, to whoſe Wiſdom and Authority the Conſtitution has entruſted ſo much, cannot by virtue of all that Power doe the greateſt or leaſt of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that Right, which, he in his private Capacity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly knows belongs, and that the Law ought to adjudge to him; and ſhall we then ſay, that, in the Kings caſe, a private Man, to whom the Law has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven no manner of Authority to judge of any ones Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, ſhall take upon him, by force, to attempt the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetling a King, who is quietly Poſſeſſed of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe <hi>he thinks</hi> another man has a better right? Is it not more agreeable to the Compariſon our Author has made, and to the Reaſon of Mankind, That where there is a National Submiſſion, in a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary way, to the Poſſeſſour of the Throne, Every pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29442:33"/> to impeach that Settlement, ought to wait for a Declaration of his Right by the States of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, till which is done, Particular Subjects, ought, with regard to common Safety and Peace, to acquieſce under the Power from which they receive Protection, and to which, by their Repreſentatives, they have <hi>Submitted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I own there may fall out very hard caſes ſometimes, upon theſe grounds, and ſuch Objections as will not receive an eaſie Anſwer: But I am ſure it will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eaſie to maintain, That the miſchiefs will be <hi>leſs</hi> in themſelves, and likely to fall out <hi>ſeldomer,</hi> than by allowing every Subject a Liberty to embroil the State, upon a pretence that the Government is not in the hands it ought to be.</p>
            <p>In matters of this kind in a <hi>mixt</hi> Monarchy, there will be ſome difficulties in the <hi>Theory,</hi> that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable. The notion of a mixt monarchy it ſelf, will not bear a ſtrict diſquiſition: For, granting that of neceſſity there muſt in all Governments be ſome laſt reſort for the final determination of all differences (which will ſeem a very reaſonable propoſition) any Man may immediately run it up to a <hi>Tyranny</hi> or <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the laſt reſort and final determination of Right or Wrong between the King and People, ſhould be agreed to be in the King; notwithſtanding all the Laws now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, he may when he pleaſes (in <hi>Theory)</hi> make his Will the ſole Law: For whenever he is minded to attempt it, after the matter's running through other hands, it comes at laſt to him to give the Rule, which is the gaining of his point. So on the other ſide, if the People are the ultimate Reſort, and ſole Judges of the Rights of their Prince, of neceſſity their deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations muſt be obeyed, tho' they determine againſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29442:33"/> his true Right. And that will in conſequence prove the Government no Monarchy, tho' he be in Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and carry the name of King, there being a Power ſuperiour to him, and to which he is accountable for his Actions. If both Prince and People are to join in it, and they differ in their Sentiments, there is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, and conſequently uncertainty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
            <p>This is the natural conſequence of driving up theſe notions to their heighth: But this is not therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day the caſe: There is a good old ſaying, that will interpoſe to ſave us: <hi>Ipſae res nolunt malè ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrari.</hi> This will, notwithſtanding all thoſe fine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, keep both the Parties from attempting <hi>ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> any thing extravagant, and utterly inconſiſtent with that mixture of Power, by which we are ruled, ſo much to our eaſe and advantage, tho' that mixture of Power can't be maintained in ſtrict reaſoning. I ſay all this to this purpoſe: I find it is ſtrongly object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to what I have advanced <hi>(viz.</hi> That a private Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject after a ſolemn ſubmiſſion of the Kingdom to an Uſurper in Title, ought not to attempt the reſtoring the <hi>King de jure,</hi> till there be ſome ſolemn deciſion in his favour, the Power of which I have placed in the States of the Kingdom) That this way of applying to the Parliament for Juſtice, and making their Claim there, may be prevented by the Uſurper's not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the States of the Kingdom to meet, or receive ſuch Claim, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I ſhould grant that they have no Power of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that purpoſe, without the conſent of the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per (which I do not;) and ſo, that this is a defect in our Laws, and one of the caſes againſt which a certain Remedy is unavoidably wanting in a mixt Monarchy; yet I may venture to ſay, That if the right of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29442:34"/> Prince be apparent, all the Attempts of the Uſurper to ſuppreſs it, will at long run prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful. We ſee the Parliament of <hi>H.</hi> 6. and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of 1660. did find Opportunities of doing right to the injured Prince; and without them the People, whether they <hi>ought</hi> or no, is one caſe; but I think I may venture to ſay they <hi>will</hi> not long bear it.</p>
            <p>If Uſurpations do put us under theſe great Difficulties, the natural Influence that the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of that will have, is, that the Nation will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto and ſuffer but very few of them; and 'tis a very unlikely thing, that the Rightful Prince ſhould be turned out without great Miſadminiſtrations. But after all, I think no one need be aſhamed of owning it to be his Opinion, That if it ſhould unhappily fall out to be the Caſe, that one of that Family to whom the Crown was at firſt limited, ſhould be injuriouſly diſpoſſeſſed of that Crown; and the reſtoring him to it, could be compaſſed by no means, but ſuch as would lay a Foundation for daily Diſturbances and Civil Wars in future Reigns, that that Perſon's Right which was given him by the Laws, ought not to be ſet in Competition with the Laws themſelves, and the Peace and Quiet of the whole Body of the People.</p>
            <p>The Conſequences which our Author draws from his Suppoſition, that <hi>Cromwell</hi> had been made King (which I confeſs would have been very miſchievous and intolerable) move me not at all. In the firſt place; notwithſtanding what he affirms, <hi>That it was almoſt come to a Concluſion that he ſhould take that Title upon him.</hi> I can't grant that there was any likelihood of his being a King in Poſſeſſion, entitled to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and benefit of this Law. Perhaps he might have made an Intereſt in ſome of the Army (though
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29442:34"/> moſt People believe the fear of their falling off from him, kept him from it) to have proclaimed him; and in the Houſe of Commons, or Parliament as they called themſelves, to have ſubmitted to him. But I have before ſaid, a bare proclaiming one <hi>King</hi> won't do the buſineſs, for then we may have as many Kings <hi>de facto</hi> as there are Rabbles of People in the Nation: But to make one who had no viſible Right before, ſuch a King <hi>de facto</hi> as may claim a Temporary Allegiance from the People, he muſt have not only the Power of the Nation in his Hands, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice in his Name; but (what <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> as he had been forced to manage matters for the getting himſelf into that monſtrous lawleſs Power he enjoyed, could never have obtained,) the Submiſſion of the <hi>remaining parts of the Conſtitution,</hi> the Lords and Commons, to him as their King and Governour. Till that is done, I know no Obligation any private man is under of paying Allegiance to ſuch a King, never having by himſelf or his Repreſentatives, ſubmitted to him. As on the other ſide, when that is done, and I receive the benefit of Protection from him, till his Poſſeſſion which protects me is loſt; or the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion which was made for me revoked and undone by an equal Power: I know nothing that can juſtifie my thinking my ſelf wiſer and more knowing than my own and the whole Peoples Repreſentatives; and from ſuch an overweening Opinion of my ſelf, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring the Diſturbance or Subverſion of a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment well and fully ſetled.</p>
            <p>But why in the ſecond place ſhould ſuch Suppoſitions of what <hi>may</hi> be, be uſed as Arguments: May we not from the Obſervation, That no inſtance like that did ever yet happen to ſet Conſcience ſo upon the Rack,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29442:35"/> reaſonably attribute ſome ſhare in the Guidance of thoſe Affairs to the Providence of a good God, who hitherto has; and, as we have reaſon from that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to hope, (unleſs by our Unthankfulneſs we draw the contrary on our ſelves) will ſtill continue to deliver us from ſuch Difficulties and Snares.</p>
            <p>If all thoſe Advantages which our Author reckons up, would have follow'd his obtaining the Crown, and if it was in his Power to have taken it when he had pleas'd, Does not the neglecting thoſe Advantages ſeem to proceed from an <hi>Infatuation,</hi> as if Providence had determined againſt him? And ought not that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſtrike an Awe and Reverence on the Minds of all People towards their preſent Majeſties Perſons and Government; every ſtep of whoſe Undertaking and Progreſs till their Advancement to the Throne, ſeems to be a Series of Providences; and the Effects of whoſe Government are ſuch, as a Man need not ſtand in fear of being taxed with Impiety, if he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the Cauſe of them immediately to God's own Hand.</p>
            <p>Before our Author comes to Anſwer Objections, (which I'll not meddle with, but leave them to ſhift for themſelves) he produces Two Arguments to prove his Aſſertion, and it would be unjuſt not to take notice <note place="margin">Caſe, <hi>f.</hi> 48.</note> of them. The firſt I have granted already, and it makes nothing againſt me. The ſecond I will but juſt mention, and leave the Reader to make his own Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon it. 'Tis the difficulty of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Caſe <hi>f.</hi> 53.</note> who is a <hi>King in Poſſeſſion:</hi> It were a great hardſhip to put the determining that upon the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ordinary Subjects, Perſons of mean Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and therefore for <hi>that</hi> Reaſon their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſhall not be due there; but 'tis nothing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29442:35"/> it of the ſame Perſons, that they be perfect Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of our Fundamental Conſtitution, and the Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the Royal Family, that they know <hi>Who it is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caſe, <hi>f.</hi> 56</note> 
               <hi>in whom the Crown is veſted, deemed, and judged hy the Law:</hi> Theſe are things more obvious to them than what they ſee and feel every day.</p>
            <p>This, Sir, I think ſufficient to be ſaid to what is ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the Laws of the Land in the <hi>Caſe</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> as far as they concern the Poſition I undertook to maintain. Perhaps the Reader may think I have copied the Author's Pattern, in offering things which ſeem to prove more than the Queſtion, according to the ſtrictneſs with which I have ſtated it, required: I am not ſenſible that I have omitted the taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of any one Argument that is materially offered from the Laws, in conttradiction to my point; I am ſure if I have, it was paſt over for want of taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, not by deſign, as what I thought could not receive an Anſwer.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, when I have ſaid this, I muſt beſpeak all the favourable Allowances your good Nature can give, to what I have written, <hi>to</hi> the ill handling a good Cauſe, that would have born a much better Defence in the ſubſtantial Parts of it; and more, <hi>to</hi> the Faults that I have been guilty of in the manner of it: An ordinary Reader would hardly pardon the latter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will think a little care might have avoided them; and I am ſenſible how guilty I am of the worſt of that kind, abundance of Repetitions; which muſt be tedious and uneaſie. All the excuſe that I can offer for my ſelf is, that the manner of writing in the way of Reflexion, (which obliges me often to take notice of the ſame Arguments uſed to different purpoſes) and not as an entire Diſcourſe, has made
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29442:36"/> that unavoidable. And, Sir, <hi>you</hi> know I have not had time enough allowed me to make it ſhort: Whoſe Fault that is <hi>You</hi> can beſt tell: And therefore, whatever others do, you in Juſtice muſt excuſe,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>Books lately Printed for</hi> William Rogers.</head>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at <hi>VVhitehall</hi> before the Queen on the Monthly Faſt Day, <hi>September</hi> 16. 1691. 4<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Perſuaſive to Frequent Communion in the Holy Sacrament of the Lord's Supper. <hi>Eighth Edition.</hi> 12<hi>mo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both by his Grace <hi>John,</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd on the <hi>28th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> at St. <hi>Andrews Holbourn,</hi> by <hi>John Moor,</hi> D. D. Biſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi> Elect, when he took his leave of that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at St. <hi>Mary le Bow,</hi> on <hi>Sunday</hi> the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> 1691. at the Conſecration of the Moſt Reverend Father in God <hi>John,</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and the Right Reverend Fathers in God, <hi>John,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Norwich, Richard,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Peterborough, Edward,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter;</hi> by <hi>Joſhua Clarke,</hi> Chaplain to the Right Reverend Father in God, the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Neceſſity of Serious Conſideration, and Speedy Repentance, as the only way to be ſafe both living and dying. By <hi>Clement Elis</hi> Rector of <hi>Kirkby</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamſhire.</hi> 80.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>VV. Petty</hi>'s Political Anatomy of <hi>Ireland.</hi> 80.</p>
            <p>The Caſe of the Allegiance due to Soveraign Powers, Stated and reſolved according to Scripture and Reaſon, and the Principles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with a more particular Reſpect to the Oath lately Enjoined of Allegiance to their Preſent Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> The <hi>6th</hi> Edition. 4<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Vindication of the Caſe of Allegiance due to Soveraign Powers, in Reply to an Anſwer to a late Phamphlet Intituled <hi>Obedience and Submiſſion to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government,</hi> demonſtrated from Biſhop <hi>Overal</hi>'s Convocation book; with a Poſtſcript in Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Sherlock's</hi> Caſe of Allegiance <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at <hi>VVhite-Hall</hi> before the Queen on the <hi>17th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1691. being the Faſt day. 4<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Practical Diſcourſe concerning Death, the fifth Edition. 8<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Practical diſcourſe concerning a Future Judgment, 80. (will be Publiſhed in a few days)</p>
            <p>Theſe five by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> Maſter of the Temple, and Chaplain in Ordinary to their Majeſties.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29442:36"/>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:29442:37"/>
            <p> LICENS'D,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>October</hi> 10. 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. Fraſer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 11. <hi>Line</hi> 16. for Nation <hi>read</hi> Notion. <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>read</hi> ſo that. <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>for</hi> trying <hi>r.</hi> ſeying. <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 23. for Majeſties, <hi>r</hi> Matters.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
